<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<countries>
<country>
	<code>au</code>
	<name>Austria</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Once the center of power for the large Austro-Hungarian Empire, Austria was reduced to a small republic after its defeat in World War I. Following annexation by Nazi Germany in 1938 and subsequent occupation by the victorious Allies in 1945, Austria's status remained unclear for a decade. A State Treaty signed in 1955 ended the occupation, recognized Austria's independence, and forbade unification with Germany. A constitutional law that same year declared the country's &quot;perpetual neutrality&quot; as a condition for Soviet military withdrawal. The Soviet Union's collapse in 1991 and Austria's entry into the European Union in 1995 have altered the meaning of this neutrality. A prosperous, democratic country, Austria entered the EU Economic and Monetary Union in 1999.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>landlocked; strategic location at the crossroads of central Europe with many easily traversable Alpine passes and valleys; major river is the Danube; population is concentrated on eastern lowlands because of steep slopes, poor soils, and low temperatures elsewhere</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central Europe, north of Italy and Slovenia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">83871</total>
			<land unit="sq km">82445</land>
			<water unit="sq km">1426</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Maine</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">0</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit=""></territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; continental, cloudy; cold winters with frequent rain and some snow in lowlands and snow in mountains; moderate summers with occasional showers</climate>
		<terrain>in the west and south mostly mountains (Alps); along the eastern and northern margins mostly flat or gently sloping</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Grossglockner 3,798 m</high>
			<low>Neusiedler See 115 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>oil, coal, lignite, timber, iron ore, copper, zinc, antimony, magnesite, tungsten, graphite, salt, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">16.59</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.85</crops>
			<other unit="%">82.56</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>landslides; avalanches; earthquakes</hazards>
		<issues>some forest degradation caused by air and soil pollution; soil pollution results from the use of agricultural chemicals; air pollution results from emissions by coal- and oil-fired power stations and industrial plants and from trucks transiting Austria between northern and southern Europe</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1170</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">84</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">3.67</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">448</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>8217</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">8.67</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.14</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">1.81</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.034</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">14</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>43</total>
			<male>41.9</male>
			<female>44</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">68</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</rate>
			<cities>VIENNA (capital) 1.693 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.051</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.01</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.71</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.95</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.32</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.23</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.35</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.78</total>
			<male unit="years">76.87</male>
			<female unit="years">82.84</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.4">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>15000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Austrian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Austrian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Austrians 91.1%, former Yugoslavs 4% (includes Croatians, Slovenes, Serbs, and Bosniaks), Turks 1.6%, German 0.9%, other or unspecified 2.4% (2001 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 73.6%, Protestant 4.7%, Muslim 4.2%, other 3.5%, unspecified 2%, none 12% (2001 census)</religions>
		<languages>German (official nationwide) 88.6%, Turkish 2.3%, Serbian 2.2%, Croatian (official in Burgenland) 1.6%, other (includes Slovene, official in Carinthia, and Hungarian, official in Burgenland) 5.3% (2001 census)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">98</total>
			<male unit=""></male>
			<female unit=""></female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">15</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.4</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Austria</long>
			<short>Austria</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>federal republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Vienna</name>
			<coordinates>48° 12' N, 16° 22' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>9 states (Bundeslaender, singular - Bundesland); Burgenland, Kaernten (Carinthia), Niederoesterreich (Lower Austria), Oberoesterreich (Upper Austria), Salzburg, Steiermark (Styria), Tirol (Tyrol), Vorarlberg, Wien (Vienna)</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>12 November 1918 (republic proclaimed); notable earlier dates: 976 (Margravate of Austria established); 17 September 1156 (Duchy of Austria founded); 11 August 1804 (Austrian Empire proclaimed)</independence>
		<national-holiday>National Day, 26 October (1955); note - commemorates the passage of the law on permanent neutrality</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system; judicial review of legislative acts by the Constitutional Court</legal-system>
		<suffrage>16 years of age; universal; note - reduced from 18 years of age in 2007</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Heinz FISCHER (SPOe) (since 8 July 2004)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Chancellor Werner FAYMANN (SPOe) (since 2 December 2008); Vice Chancellor Michael SPINDELEGGER (OeVP) (since 21 April 2011)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers chosen by the president on the advice of the chancellor</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected for a six-year term (eligible for a second term) by direct popular vote and formally sworn into office before the Federal Assembly or Bundesversammlung; presidential election last held on 25 April 2010 (next to be held on 25 April 2016); chancellor formally chosen by the president but determined by the coalition parties forming a parliamentary majority; vice chancellor chosen by the president on the advice of the chancellor</elections>
			<election-results>Heinz FISCHER reelected president; percent of vote - Heinz FISCHER 79.33%, Barbara ROSENKRANZ 15.24%, Rudolf GEHRING 5.43%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Federal Assembly or Bundesversammlung consists of Federal Council or Bundesrat (62 seats; delegates appointed by state parliaments with each state receiving 3 to 12 seats in proportion to its population; members serve five- or six-year terms) and the National Council or Nationalrat (183 seats; members elected by popular vote for a five-year term under a system of proportional representation with partially-open party lists)</description>
			<elections>National Council - last held on 28 September 2008 (next to be held by September 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>National Council - percent of vote by party - SPOe 29.3%, OeVP 26%, FPOe 17.5%, BZOe 10.7%, Greens 10.4%, other 6.1%; seats by party - SPOe 57, OeVP 51, FPOe 34, BZOe 21, Greens 20; note - seats by party since 2010 - SPOe 57, OeVP 51, FPOe 39, BZOe 16, Greens 20</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Judicial Court or Oberster Gerichtshof; Administrative Court or Verwaltungsgerichtshof; Constitutional Court or Verfassungsgerichtshof</judicial>
		<parties>Alliance for the Future of Austria or BZOe [Josef BUCHER]; Austrian People's Party or OeVP [Josef PROELL]; Freedom Party of Austria or FPOe [Heinz Christian STRACHE]; Social Democratic Party of Austria or SPOe [Werner FAYMANN]; The Greens [Eva GLAWISCHNIG]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Australia Group, BIS, BSEC (observer), CE, CEI, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-9, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF (observer), OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PFP, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNDOF, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNHCR, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Christian PROSL</chief>
			<chancery>3524 International Court NW, Washington, DC 20008-3035</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 895-6700</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 895-6750</FAX>
			<consulates>Chicago, Los Angeles, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador William C. EACHO III</chief>
			<embassy>Boltzmanngasse 16, A-1090, Vienna</embassy>
			<mailing-address>use embassy street address</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[43] (1) 31339-0</telephone>
			<FAX>[43] (1) 3100682</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal horizontal bands of red (top), white, and red; the flag design is certainly one of the oldest - if not the oldest - national banners in the world; according to tradition, in 1191, following a fierce battle in the Third Crusade, Duke Leopold V of Austria's white tunic became completely blood-spattered; upon removal of his wide belt or sash, a white band was revealed; the red-white-red color combination was subsequently adopted as his banner</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Bundeshymne&quot; (Federal Hymn)</name>
			<by>Paula von PRERADOVIC/Wolfgang Amadeus MOZART or Johann HOLZER (disputed)</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Austria, with its well-developed market economy and high standard of living, is closely tied to other EU economies, especially Germany's. Its economy features a large service sector, a sound industrial sector, and a small, but highly developed agricultural sector. Following several years of solid foreign demand for Austrian exports and record employment growth, the international financial crisis and global economic downturn in 2008 led to a sharp but brief recession. Austrian GDP contracted 3.9% in 2009 but saw positive growth of about 2% in 2010. Unemployment has not risen as steeply in Austria as elsewhere in Europe, partly because its government has subsidized reduced working hour schemes to allow companies to retain employees. Stabilization measures, stimulus spending, and an income tax reform pushed the budget deficit to 3.5% of GDP in 2009 and 4.7% in 2010, from only about 1.3% in 2008. The international financial crisis caused difficulties for Austria's largest banks whose extensive operations in central, eastern, and southeastern Europe faced large losses. The government provided bank support - including in some instances, nationalization - to prevent insolvency and possible contagion. In the medium-term all large Austrian banks will need additional capital. Even after the global economic outlook improves, Austria will need to continue restructuring, emphasize knowledge-based sectors of the economy, and encourage greater labor flexibility and labor participation to offset growing unemployment and Austria's aging population and low fertility rate.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>376800000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">2</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>3700000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">4.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">70.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.9</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">4.82</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">402800000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">659200000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grains, potatoes, wine, fruit; dairy products, cattle, pigs, poultry; lumber</agriculture-products>
		<industries>construction, machinery, vehicles and parts, food, metals, chemicals, lumber and wood processing, paper and paperboard, communications equipment, tourism</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>68850000000</production>
			<consumption>65670000000</consumption>
			<exports>18760000000</exports>
			<imports>19540000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">21880</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">247700</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">50410</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">273000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">89000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">1580000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">8130000000.000001</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">3961000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">9460000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">24800000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, motor vehicles and parts, paper and paperboard, metal goods, chemicals, iron and steel, textiles, foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 30.96%, Italy 8.17%, Switzerland 4.99%, US 3.99% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">156000000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, motor vehicles, chemicals, metal goods, oil and oil products; foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 45.07%, Switzerland 6.76%, Italy 6.66%, Netherlands 4.03% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">755000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>highly developed and efficient</assessment>
			<domestic>fixed-line subscribership has been in decline since the mid-1990s with mobile-cellular subscribership eclipsing it by the late 1990s; the fiber-optic net is very extensive; all telephone applications and Internet services are available</domestic>
			<international>country code - 43; satellite earth stations - 15; in addition, there are about 600 VSATs (very small aperture terminals) (2007)</international>
			<land-lines>3253000</land-lines>
			<mobile>11773000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>Austria's public broadcaster, ORF, was the main broadcast source until commercial radio and television service was introduced in the 1990s; cable and satellite TV are available, including German TV stations (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.at</tld>
			<hosts>3266000</hosts>
			<users>6143000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>55</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">4</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Enns, Krems, Linz, Vienna</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Land Forces (KdoLdSK), Air Forces (KdoLuSK)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>1941</male>
				<female>1910</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1579</male>
				<female>1554</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>48108</male>
				<female>45752</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs>transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin and South American cocaine destined for Western Europe; increasing consumption of European-produced synthetic drugs</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>be</code>
	<name>Belgium</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Belgium became independent from the Netherlands in 1830; it was occupied by Germany during World Wars I and II. The country prospered in the past half century as a modern, technologically advanced European state and member of NATO and the EU. Tensions between the Dutch-speaking Flemings of the north and the French-speaking Walloons of the south have led in recent years to constitutional amendments granting these regions formal recognition and autonomy.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>crossroads of Western Europe; most West European capitals within 1,000 km of Brussels, the seat of both the European Union and NATO</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western Europe, bordering the North Sea, between France and the Netherlands</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">30528</total>
			<land unit="sq km">30278</land>
			<water unit="sq km">250</water>
			<comparison>about the size of Maryland</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">66.5</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>median line with neighbors</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; mild winters, cool summers; rainy, humid, cloudy</climate>
		<terrain>flat coastal plains in northwest, central rolling hills, rugged mountains of Ardennes Forest in southeast</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Botrange 694 m</high>
			<low>North Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>construction materials, silica sand, carbonates</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">27.42</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.69</crops>
			<other unit="%">71.89</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>flooding is a threat along rivers and in areas of reclaimed coastal land, protected from the sea by concrete dikes</hazards>
		<issues>the environment is exposed to intense pressures from human activities: urbanization, dense transportation network, industry, extensive animal breeding and crop cultivation; air and water pollution also have repercussions for neighboring countries; uncertainties regarding federal and regional responsibilities (now resolved) had slowed progress in tackling environmental challenges</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">230</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">20.8</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">7.44</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">714</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>10431</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.06</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.57</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">1.22</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.071</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.9</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>42.3</total>
			<male>41</male>
			<female>43.6</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">97</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.4</rate>
			<cities>BRUSSELS (capital) 1.892 million; Antwerp 961,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.045</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.71</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.33</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.86</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.78</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.51</total>
			<male unit="years">76.35</male>
			<female unit="years">82.81</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.65">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>14000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Belgian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Belgian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Fleming 58%, Walloon 31%, mixed or other 11%</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 75%, other (includes Protestant) 25%</religions>
		<languages>Dutch (official) 60%, French (official) 40%, German (official) less than 1%, legally bilingual (Dutch and French)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">6.01</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Belgium</long>
			<short>Belgium</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>federal parliamentary democracy under a constitutional monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Brussels</name>
			<coordinates>50° 50' N, 4° 20' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>4 October 1830 (a provisional government declared independence from the Netherlands); 21 July 1831 (King LEOPOLD I ascended to the throne)</independence>
		<national-holiday>21 July (1831) ascension to the Throne of King LEOPOLD I</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on the French Civil Code; note - Belgian law continues to be modified in conformance with the legislative norms mandated by the European Union; judicial review of legislative acts</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal and compulsory</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King ALBERT II (since 9 August 1993); Heir Apparent Prince PHILIPPE, son of the monarch</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Yves LETERME (since 25 November 2009); note - the king accepted the resignation of LETERME on 26 April 2010; LETERME remains as caretaker</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers are formally appointed by the monarch</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary and constitutional; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually appointed prime minister by the monarch and then approved by parliament</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament consists of a Senate or Senaat in Dutch, Senat in French (71 seats; 40 members directly elected by popular vote, 31 indirectly elected; members serve four-year terms) and a Chamber of Deputies or Kamer van Volksvertegenwoordigers in Dutch, Chambre des Representants in French (150 seats; members directly elected by popular vote on the basis of proportional representation to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate and Chamber of Deputies - last held on 13 June 2010 (next to be held no later than June 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - N-VA 19.6%, PS 13.6%, CD&amp;V 10%, sp.a 9.5%, MR 9.3%, Open VLD 8.2%, VB 7.6%, Ecolo 5.5%, CDH 5.1% Groen! 3.9%, other 7.7%; seats by party - N-VA 9, PS 7, CD&amp;V 4, sp.a 4, MR 4, Open VLD 4, VB 3, Ecolo 2, CDH 2, Groen! 1; Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by party - N-VA 17.4%, PS 13.7%, CD&amp;V 10.9%, MR 9.3%, sp.a 9.2%, Open VLD 8.6%, VB 7.8%, CDH 5.5%, Ecolo 4.8%, Groen! 4.4%, List Dedecker 2.3%, the Popular Party 1.3%, other 4.8%; seats by party - N-VA 27, PS 26, CD&amp;V 17, MR 18, sp.a 13, Open VLD 13, VB 12, CDH 9, Ecolo 8, Groen! 5, List Dedecker 1, the Popular Party 1</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Constitutional Court (previously Court of Arbitration) (12 judges, 6 Dutch-speaking and 6 French-speaking, appointed by the King); Supreme Court of Justice or Hof van Cassatie (in Dutch) or Cour de Cassation (in French) (judges are appointed for life by the government; candidacies have to be submitted by the High Justice Council)</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional members), AfDB (nonregional members), Australia Group, Benelux, BIS, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-9, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNTSO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jan MATTHYSEN</chief>
			<chancery>3330 Garfield Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 333-6900</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 333-3079</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Los Angeles, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Howard W. GUTMAN</chief>
			<embassy>27 Boulevard du Regent [Regentlaan], B-1000 Brussels</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 82, Box 002, APO AE 09710</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[32] (2) 508-2111</telephone>
			<FAX>[32] (2) 511-2725</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal vertical bands of black (hoist side), yellow, and red; the vertical design was based on the flag of France; the colors are those of the arms of the duchy of Brabant (yellow lion with red claws and tongue on a black field)</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;La Brabanconne&quot; (The Song of Brabant)</name>
			<by>Louis-Alexandre DECHET[French] Victor CEULEMANS [Dutch]/Francois VAN CAMPENHOUT</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>This modern, open, and private-enterprise-based economy has capitalized on its central geographic location, highly developed transport network, and diversified industrial and commercial base. Industry is concentrated mainly in the more heavily-populated region of Flanders in the north. With few natural resources, Belgium imports substantial quantities of raw materials and exports a large volume of manufactures, making its economy vulnerable to volatility in world markets, yet also able to benefit from them. Roughly three-quarters of Belgium's trade is with other EU countries, and Belgium has benefited most from its proximity to Germany. In 2010 Belgian GDP grew by 2.1%, the unemployment rate rose slightly, and the government reduced the budget deficit, which had worsened in 2008 and 2009 because of large-scale bail-outs in the financial sector. Belgium's budget deficit decreased from 6% of GDP to 4.8% in 2010, while public debt was just under 100% of GDP. Belgian banks were severely affected by the international financial crisis with three major banks receiving capital injections from the government. An ageing population and rising social expenditures are mid- to long-term challenges to public finances.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>465700000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">2</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>5020000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">8.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">98.6</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">2.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">6.15</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">539400000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">801100000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>sugar beets, fresh vegetables, fruits, grain, tobacco; beef, veal, pork, milk</agriculture-products>
		<industries>engineering and metal products, motor vehicle assembly, transportation equipment, scientific instruments, processed food and beverages, chemicals, basic metals, textiles, glass, petroleum</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>82170000000</production>
			<consumption>84880000000</consumption>
			<exports>6561000000</exports>
			<imports>17160000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">11220</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">608200</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">433700</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">1120000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">16870000000.000002</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">16780000000.000002</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, chemicals, finished diamonds, metals and metal products, foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 19.58%, France 17.71%, Netherlands 11.84%, UK 7.21%, US 5.37%, Italy 4.77% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">281700000000</total>
			<commodities>raw materials, machinery and equipment, chemicals, raw diamonds, pharmaceuticals, foodstuffs, transportation equipment, oil products</commodities>
			<partners>Netherlands 17.93%, Germany 17.14%, France 11.69%, Ireland 6.26%, US 5.74%, UK 5.07%, China 4.09% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">1241000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>highly developed, technologically advanced, and completely automated domestic and international telephone and telegraph facilities</assessment>
			<domestic>nationwide mobile-cellular telephone system; extensive cable network; limited microwave radio relay network</domestic>
			<international>country code - 32; landing point for a number of submarine cables that provide links to Europe, the Middle East, and Asia; satellite earth stations - 7 (Intelsat - 3) (2007)</international>
			<land-lines>4255000</land-lines>
			<mobile>12419000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a segmented market with the three major communities (Flemish, French, and German-speaking) each having responsibility for their own broadcast media; multiple TV channels exist for each community; additionally, in excess of 90% of households are connected to cable and can access broadcasts of TV stations from neighboring countries; each community has a public radio network co-existing with private broadcasters (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.be</tld>
			<hosts>4465000</hosts>
			<users>8113000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>43</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>[object Object]</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Belgian Armed Forces: Land Operations Command, Naval Operations Command, Air Operations Commands (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2359</male>
				<female>2291</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1934</male>
				<female>1877</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>59665</male>
				<female>57142</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs>growing producer of synthetic drugs and cannabis; transit point for US-bound ecstasy; source of precursor chemicals for South American cocaine processors; transshipment point for cocaine, heroin, hashish, and marijuana entering Western Europe; despite a strengthening of legislation, the country remains vulnerable to money laundering related to narcotics, automobiles, alcohol, and tobacco; significant domestic consumption of ecstasy</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>fi</code>
	<name>Finland</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Finland was a province and then a grand duchy under Sweden from the 12th to the 19th centuries, and an autonomous grand duchy of Russia after 1809. It won its complete independence in 1917. During World War II, it was able to successfully defend its freedom and resist invasions by the Soviet Union - albeit with some loss of territory. In the subsequent half century, the Finns made a remarkable transformation from a farm/forest economy to a diversified modern industrial economy; per capita income is now among the highest in Western Europe. A member of the European Union since 1995, Finland was the only Nordic state to join the euro system at its initiation in January 1999. In the 21st century, the key features of Finland's modern welfare state are a high standard of education, equality promotion, and national social security system - currently challenged by an aging population and the fluctuations of an export-driven economy.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>long boundary with Russia; Helsinki is northernmost national capital on European continent; population concentrated on small southwestern coastal plain</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Europe, bordering the Baltic Sea, Gulf of Bothnia, and Gulf of Finland, between Sweden and Russia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">338145</total>
			<land unit="sq km">303815</land>
			<water unit="sq km">34330</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Montana</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">1250</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>cold temperate; potentially subarctic but comparatively mild because of moderating influence of the North Atlantic Current, Baltic Sea, and more than 60,000 lakes</climate>
		<terrain>mostly low, flat to rolling plains interspersed with lakes and low hills</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Haltiatunturi 1,328 m</high>
			<low>Baltic Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>timber, iron ore, copper, lead, zinc, chromite, nickel, gold, silver, limestone</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">6.54</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.02</crops>
			<other unit="%">93.44</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>NA</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution from manufacturing and power plants contributing to acid rain; water pollution from industrial wastes, agricultural chemicals; habitat loss threatens wildlife populations</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">770</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">110</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">2.33</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">444</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>5259</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.37</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.24</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0.62</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.075</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">16</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>42.5</total>
			<male>40.8</male>
			<female>44.3</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">85</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</rate>
			<cities>HELSINKI (capital) 1.107 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.04</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.69</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.43</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.73</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.11</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.27</total>
			<male unit="years">75.79</male>
			<female unit="years">82.89</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.73">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>2600</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Finn(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Finnish</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Finn 93.4%, Swede 5.6%, Russian 0.5%, Estonian 0.3%, Roma (Gypsy) 0.1%, Sami 0.1% (2006)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Lutheran Church of Finland 82.5%, Orthodox Church 1.1%, other Christian 1.1%, other 0.1%, none 15.1% (2006)</religions>
		<languages>Finnish (official) 91.2%, Swedish (official) 5.5%, other (small Sami- and Russian-speaking minorities) 3.3% (2007)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">100</total>
			<male unit="%">100</male>
			<female unit="%">100</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">17</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.9</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Republic of Finland</long>
			<short>Finland</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Helsinki</name>
			<coordinates>60° 10' N, 24° 56' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+2 (7 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>19 regions (maakunnat, singular - maakunta (Finnish); landskapen, singular - landskapet (Swedish)); Aland (Swedish), Ahvenanmaa (Finnish); Etela-Karjala (Finnish), Sodra Karelen (Swedish) [South Karelia]; Etela-Pohjanmaa (Finnish), Sodra Osterbotten (Swedish) [South Ostrobothnia]; Etela-Savo (Finnish), Sodra Savolax (Swedish) [South Savo]; Kanta-Hame (Finnish), Egentliga Tavastland (Swedish); Kainuu (Finnish), Kajanaland (Swedish); Keski-Pohjanmaa (Finnish), Mellersta Osterbotten (Swedish) [Central Ostrobothnia]; Keski-Suomi (Finnish), Mellersta Finland (Swedish) [Central Finland]; Kymenlaakso (Finnish), Kymmenedalen (Swedish); Lappi (Finnish), Lappland (Swedish); Paijat-Hame (Finnish), Paijanne-Tavastland (Swedish); Pirkanmaa (Finnish), Birkaland (Swedish) [Tampere]; Osterbotten (Swedish), Pohjanmaa (Finnish) [Ostrobothnia]; Pohjois-Karjala (Finnish), Norra Karelen (Swedish) [North Karelia]; Pohjois-Pohjanmaa (Finnish), Norra Osterbotten (Swedish) [North Ostrobothnia]; Pohjois-Savo (Finnish), Norra Savolax (Swedish) [North Savo]; Satakunta (Finnish and Swedish); Uusimaa (Finnish), Nyland (Swedish) [Newland]; Varsinais-Suomi (Finnish), Egentliga Finland (Swedish) [Southwest Finland]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>6 December 1917 (from Russia)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 6 December (1917)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on the Swedish model; note - the president may request the Supreme Court to review laws</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Tarja HALONEN (since 1 March 2000)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Mari KIVINIEMI (since 22 June 2010); Deputy Prime Minister Jyrki KATAINEN (since 19 April 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of State or Valtioneuvosto appointed by the president, responsible to parliament</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a six-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 15 January 2006 (next to be held in January 2012); the parliament elects a prime minister who is then appointed to office by the president; Prime Minister KIVINIEMI elected on 22 June 2010</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote - Tarja HALONEN (SDP) 46.3%, Sauli NIINISTO (Kok) 24.1%, Matti VANHANEN (Kesk) 18.6%, Heidi HAUTALA (VIHR) 3.5% other 10.5%; a runoff election between HALONEN and NIINISTO was held 29 January 2006 - HALONEN 51.8%, NIINISTO 48.2%; Mari KIVINIEMI elected prime minister; election results 115-56</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral Parliament or Eduskunta (200 seats; members elected by popular vote on a proportional basis to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 17 April 2011 (next to be held in April 2015)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - Kok 20.4%, SDP 19.1%, True Finns 19%, Kesk 15.8%, VAS 8.1%, VIHR 7.2%, SFP 4.3%, KD 4%, other 2%; seats by party - Kok 44, SDP 42, True Finns 39, Kesk 35, VAS 14, VIHR 10, SFP 9, KD 6, other 1 (the constituency of Aland)</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>general courts - deal with criminal and civil cases (include district courts, Courts of Appeal, and the Supreme Court or Korkein Oikeus, whose judges are appointed by the president); administrative courts</judicial>
		<parties>Center Party or Kesk [Mari KIVINIEMI]; Christian Democrats or KD [Paivi RASANEN]; Green Party or VIHR [Anni SINNEMAKI]; Left Alliance or VAS [Paavo ARHINMAKI]; National Coalition Party or Kok [Jyrki KATAINEN]; Social Democratic Party or SDP [Jutta URPILAINEN]; Swedish People's Party or SFP [Stefan WALLIN]; True Finns or PS [Timo SOINI]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council, Australia Group, BIS, CBSS, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-9, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NC, NEA, NIB, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PFP, Schengen Convention, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNMOGIP, UNRWA, UNTSO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Pekka LINTU</chief>
			<chancery>3301 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 298-5800</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 298-6030</FAX>
			<consulates>Los Angeles, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Bruce J. ORECK</chief>
			<embassy>Itainen Puistotie 14B, 00140 Helsinki</embassy>
			<mailing-address>APO AE 09723</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[358] (9) 616250</telephone>
			<FAX>[358] (9) 6162 5800</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>white with a blue cross extending to the edges of the flag; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side in the style of the Dannebrog (Danish flag); the blue represents the thousands of lakes scattered across the country, while the white is for the snow that covers the land in winter</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Maamme&quot; (Our Land)</name>
			<by>Johan Ludvig RUNEBERG/Fredrik PACIUS</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Finland has a highly industrialized, largely free-market economy with per capita output roughly that of Austria, Belgium, the Netherlands, and Sweden. Trade is important with exports accounting for over one third of GDP in recent years. Finland is strongly competitive in manufacturing - principally the wood, metals, engineering, telecommunications, and electronics industries. Finland excels in high-tech exports such as mobile phones. Except for timber and several minerals, Finland depends on imports of raw materials, energy, and some components for manufactured goods. Because of the climate, agricultural development is limited to maintaining self-sufficiency in basic products. Forestry, an important export earner, provides a secondary occupation for the rural population. Finland had been one of the best performing economies within the EU in recent years and its banks and financial markets avoided the worst of global financial crisis. However, the world slowdown hit exports and domestic demand hard in 2009, with Finland experiencing one of the deepest contractions in the euro zone. A recovery of exports, domestic trade, and household consumption stimulated economic growth in 2010. The recession left a deep mark on general government finances and the debt ratio, turning previously strong budget surpluses into deficits. Despite good growth prospects, general government finances will remain in deficit during the next few years. The great challenge of economic policy will be to implement a post-recession exit strategy in which measures supporting growth will be combined with general government adjustment measures. Longer-term, Finland must address a rapidly aging population and decreasing productivity that threaten competitiveness, fiscal sustainability, and economic growth.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>239200000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">3.1</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>2680000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">8.4</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">45.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.2</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">3.51</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">160400000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">259200000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>barley, wheat, sugar beets, potatoes; dairy cattle; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>metals and metal products, electronics, machinery and scientific instruments, shipbuilding, pulp and paper, foodstuffs, chemicals, textiles, clothing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>77440000000</production>
			<consumption>87250000000</consumption>
			<exports>3335000000</exports>
			<imports>16110000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">8718</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">206200</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">130500</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">337900</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit=""></production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">4288999999.9999995</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">4288999999.9999995</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>electrical and optical equipment, machinery, transport equipment, paper and pulp, chemicals, basic metals; timber</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 10.32%, Sweden 9.79%, Russia 9%, US 7.85%, Netherlands 5.9%, UK 5.24%, China 4.1% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">69110000000</total>
			<commodities>foodstuffs, petroleum and petroleum products, chemicals, transport equipment, iron and steel, machinery, textile yarn and fabrics, grains</commodities>
			<partners>Russia 16.28%, Germany 15.76%, Sweden 14.65%, Netherlands 6.99%, China 5.29%, France 4.22% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">370800000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>modern system with excellent service</assessment>
			<domestic>digital fiber-optic fixed-line network and an extensive mobile-cellular network provide domestic needs</domestic>
			<international>country code - 358; submarine cables provide links to Estonia and Sweden; satellite earth stations - access to Intelsat transmission service via a Swedish satellite earth station, 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic and Indian Ocean regions); note - Finland shares the Inmarsat earth station with the other Nordic countries (Denmark, Iceland, Norway, and Sweden)</international>
			<land-lines>1430000</land-lines>
			<mobile>7700000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a mix of publicly-operated TV stations and privately-owned TV stations; the 2 publicly-owned TV stations recently expanded services and the largest private TV station has introduced several special-interest pay-TV channels; cable and satellite multi-channel subscription services are available; all TV signals have been broadcast digitally since September 2007; analog broadcasts via cable networks were terminated in February 2008; public broadcasting maintains a network of 13 national and 25 regional radio stations; a large number of private radio broadcasters (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.fi; note - Aland Islands assigned .ax</tld>
			<hosts>4394000</hosts>
			<users>4393000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>148</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">26</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">10</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">22</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Helsinki, Kotka, Naantali, Porvoo, Raahe, Rauma</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Finnish Defense Forces (FDF): Army, Navy (includes Coastal Defense Forces), Air Force (Suomen Ilmavoimat) (2007)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>1155</male>
				<female>1106</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>955151</male>
				<female>912983</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>32599</male>
				<female>31416</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>various groups in Finland advocate restoration of Karelia and other areas ceded to the Soviet Union, but the Finnish Government asserts no territorial demands</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>fr</code>
	<name>France</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Although ultimately a victor in World Wars I and II, France suffered extensive losses in its empire, wealth, manpower, and rank as a dominant nation-state. Nevertheless, France today is one of the most modern countries in the world and is a leader among European nations. Since 1958, it has constructed a hybrid presidential-parliamentary governing system resistant to the instabilities experienced in earlier more purely parliamentary administrations. In recent decades, its reconciliation and cooperation with Germany have proved central to the economic integration of Europe, including the introduction of a common exchange currency, the euro, in January 1999. In the early 21st century, five French overseas entities - French Guiana, Guadeloupe, Martinique, Mayotte, and Reunion - became French regions and were made part of France proper.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>largest West European nation</note>
		<location>
			<desc>[object Object]</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">551500</total>
			<land unit=""></land>
			<water unit=""></water>
			<comparison>slightly less than the size of Texas</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit=""></coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>[object Object]</climate>
		<terrain>[object Object]</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mont Blanc 4,807 m</high>
			<low>Rhone River delta -2 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>[object Object]</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">33.46</arable>
			<crops unit="%">2.03</crops>
			<other unit="%">64.51</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>some forest damage from acid rain; air pollution from industrial and vehicle emissions; water pollution from urban wastes, agricultural runoff</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit=""></irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">189</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">33.16</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">548</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>65312</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">12.29</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">8.76</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">1.46</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.5</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">18.5</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">64.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>39.9</total>
			<male>38.4</male>
			<female>41.5</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">85</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1</rate>
			<cities>PARIS (capital) 10.41 million; Marseille-Aix-en-Provence 1.457 million; Lyon 1.456 million; Lille 1.028 million; Nice-Cannes 977,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.051</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.72</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.29</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.61</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">2.96</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.19</total>
			<male unit="years">78.02</male>
			<female unit="years">84.54</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.96">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>150000</total>
			<deaths>1700</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Frenchman(men), Frenchwoman(women)</noun>
			<adjective>French</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>[object Object]</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>[object Object]</religions>
		<languages>French</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.6</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>French Republic</long>
			<short>France</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Paris</name>
			<coordinates>48° 52' N, 2° 20' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>no official date of independence: 486 (Frankish tribes unified under Merovingian kingship); 10 August 843 (Western Francia established from the division of the Carolingian Empire); 14 July 1789 (French monarchy overthrown); 22 September 1792 (First French Republic founded); 4 October 1958 (Fifth French Republic established)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Fete de la Federation, 14 July (1790); note - although often incorrectly referred to as Bastille Day, the celebration actually commemorates the holiday held on the first anniversary of the storming of the Bastille (on 14 July 1789) and the establishment of a constitutional monarchy; other names for the holiday are Fete Nationale (National Holiday) and quatorze juillet (14th of July)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law; review of administrative but not legislative acts</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Nicolas SARKOZY (since 16 May 2007)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Francois FILLON (since 17 May 2007)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the president at the suggestion of the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by popular vote for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 22 April and 6 May 2007 (next to be held in the spring of 2012); prime minister appointed by the president</elections>
			<election-results>Nicolas SARKOZY elected; first round: percent of vote - Nicolas SARKOZY 31.2%, Segolene ROYAL 25.9%, Francois BAYROU 18.6%, Jean-Marie LE PEN 10.4%, others 13.9%; second round: SARKOZY 53.1%, ROYAL 46.9%</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament or Parlement consists of the Senate or Senat (343 seats; 323 for metropolitan France and overseas departments, 2 for New Caledonia, 2 for French Polynesia, 1 for Saint-Pierre and Miquelon, 1 for Saint-Barthelemy, 1 for Saint-Martin, 1 for Wallis and Futuna, and 12 for French nationals abroad; members indirectly elected by an electoral college to serve six-year terms; one third elected every three years); note - between 2006 and 2011, 15 new seats will be added to the Senate for a total of 348 seats - 328 for metropolitan France and overseas departments, 2 for New Caledonia, 2 for French Polynesia, 1 for Saint-Pierre and Miquelon, 1 for Saint-Barthelemy, 1 for Saint-Martin, 1 for Wallis and Futuna, and 12 for French nationals abroad; Mayotte's previously held 2 seats as an overseas collectivity are now included in the total as an overseas department; starting in 2008, members will be indirectly elected by an electoral college to serve six-year terms with one-half elected every three years; and the National Assembly or Assemblee Nationale (577 seats; 555 for metropolitan France, 15 for overseas departments, 7 for overseas dependencies; members elected by popular vote under a single-member majority system to serve five-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 21 September 2008 (next to be held in September 2011); National Assembly - last held on 10 and 17 June 2007 (next to be held in June 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - UMP 151, PS 102, PCF 22, MoDem 11, NC 11, Greens 5, PG 2, other 39; National Assembly - percent of vote by party - UMP 46.4%, PS 42.2%, miscellaneous left wing parties 2.5%, PCF 2.3%, NC 2.1%, PRG 1.6%, miscellaneous right wing parties 1.2%, the Greens 0.4%, other 1.2%; seats by party - UMP 313, PS 186, NC 22, miscellaneous left wing parties 15, PCF 16, miscellaneous right wing parties 9, PRG 7, the Greens 3, other 6</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court of Appeals or Cour de Cassation (judges are appointed by the president from nominations of the High Council of the Judiciary); Constitutional Council or Conseil Constitutionnel (three members appointed by the president, three appointed by the president of the National Assembly, and three appointed by the president of the Senate); Council of State or Conseil d'Etat</judicial>
		<parties>Democratic Movement or MoDem [Francois BAYROU] (previously Union for French Democracy or UDF); French Communist Party or PCF [Pierre LAURENT]; Greens [Cecile DUFLOT]; Left Party or PG [Jean-Luc MELENCHON]; Left Radical Party or PRG [Jean-Michel BAYLET] (previously Radical Socialist Party or PRS and the Left Radical Movement or MRG); Movement for France or MPF [Philippe DE VILLIERS]; National Front or FN [Jean-Marie LE PEN]; New Anticapitalist Party or NPA [Olivier BESANCENOT]; New Center or NC [Herve MORIN]; Radical Party [Jean-Louis BORLOO]; Rally for France or RPF [Charles PASQUA]; Republican and Citizen Movement or MRC [Jean Pierre CHEVENEMENT]; Socialist Party or PS [Martine AUBRY]; Union for a Popular Movement or UMP [Jean-Francois COPE]; Worker's Struggle or LO [Nathalie ARTHAUD]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, BDEAC, BIS, BSEC (observer), CBSS (observer), CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, FZ, G-20, G-5, G-7, G-8, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, InOC, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSTAH, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PIF (partner), Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), SPC, UN, UN Security Council, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, Union Latina, UNITAR, UNMIL, UNOCI, UNRWA, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Francois M. DELATTRE</chief>
			<chancery>4101 Reservoir Road NW, Washington, DC 20007</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 944-6000</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 944-6166</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New Orleans, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Charles H. RIVKIN</chief>
			<embassy>2 Avenue Gabriel, 75382 Paris Cedex 08</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 116, APO AE 09777</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[33] (1) 43-12-22-22</telephone>
			<FAX>[33] (1) 42 66 97 83</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;La Marseillaise&quot; (The Song of Marseille)</name>
			<by>Claude-Joseph ROUGET de Lisle</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>France is in the midst of transition from a well-to-do modern economy that has featured extensive government ownership and intervention to one that relies more on market mechanisms. The government has partially or fully privatized many large companies, banks, and insurers, and has ceded stakes in such leading firms as Air France, France Telecom, Renault, and Thales. It maintains a strong presence in some sectors, particularly power, public transport, and defense industries. With at least 75 million foreign tourists per year, France is the most visited country in the world and maintains the third largest income in the world from tourism. France's leaders remain committed to a capitalism in which they maintain social equity by means of laws, tax policies, and social spending that reduce income disparity and the impact of free markets on public health and welfare. France has weathered the global economic crisis better than most other big EU economies because of the relative resilience of domestic consumer spending, a large public sector, and less exposure to the downturn in global demand than in some other countries. Nonetheless, France's real GDP contracted 2.5% in 2009, but recovered somewhat in 2010, while the unemployment rate increased from 7.4% in 2008 to 9.5% in 2010. The government pursuit of aggressive stimulus and investment measures in response to the economic crisis, however, are contributing to a deterioration of France's public finances. The government budget deficit rose sharply from 3.4% of GDP in 2008 to 7.8% of GDP in 2010, while France's public debt rose from 68% of GDP to 84% over the same period. Paris is terminating stimulus measures, eliminating tax credits, and freezing most government spending to bring the budget deficit under the 3% euro-zone ceiling by 2013, and to highlight France's commitment to fiscal discipline at a time of intense financial market scrutiny of euro zone debt levels. President SARKOZY - who secured passage of pension reform in 2010 - is expected to seek passage of some tax reforms in 2011, but he may delay additional, more costly, reforms until after the 2012 election.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>2583000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>28210000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">9.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">83.5</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">7.46</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">2292000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">4319000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, cereals, sugar beets, potatoes, wine grapes; beef, dairy products; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>machinery, chemicals, automobiles, metallurgy, aircraft, electronics; textiles, food processing; tourism</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>535700000000.00006</production>
			<consumption>447200000000</consumption>
			<exports>58690000000</exports>
			<imports>10680000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">70820</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">1875000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">597800</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">2386000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">101200000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">877000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">44840000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">1931000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">45850000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">7079000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and transportation equipment, aircraft, plastics, chemicals, pharmaceutical products, iron and steel, beverages</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 15.88%, Italy 8.16%, Spain 7.8%, Belgium 7.44%, UK 7.04%, US 5.65%, Netherlands 3.99% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">577700000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, vehicles, crude oil, aircraft, plastics, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 19.41%, Belgium 11.61%, Italy 7.97%, Netherlands 7.15%, Spain 6.68%, UK 4.9%, US 4.72%, China 4.44% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">4698000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>highly developed</assessment>
			<domestic>extensive cable and microwave radio relay; extensive use of fiber-optic cable; domestic satellite system</domestic>
			<international>country code - 33; numerous submarine cables provide links throughout Europe, Asia, Australia, the Middle East, and US; satellite earth stations - more than 3 (2 Intelsat (with total of 5 antennas - 2 for Indian Ocean and 3 for Atlantic Ocean), NA Eutelsat, 1 Inmarsat - Atlantic Ocean region); HF radiotelephone communications with more than 20 countries</international>
			<land-lines>36.441 million; 35.5 million (metropolitan France) (2009)</land-lines>
			<mobile>60.95 million; 59.543 million (metropolitan France) (2009)</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a mix of both publicly-operated and privately-owned TV stations; state-owned France Televisions operates 4 networks, one of which is a network of regional stations, and has part-interest in several thematic cable/satellite channels and international channels; a large number of privately-owned regional and local TV stations; multi-channel satellite and cable services provide a large number of channels; public broadcaster Radio France operates 7 national networks, a series of regional networks, and operates services for overseas territories and foreign audiences; Radio France Internationale (RFI), under the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, is a leading international broadcaster; a large number of commercial FM stations, with many of them consolidating into commercial networks (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>metropolitan France - .fr; French Guiana - .gf; Guadeloupe - .gp; Martinique - .mq; Mayotte - .yt; Reunion - .re</tld>
			<hosts>15,182,001; 15.161 million (metropolitan France) (2010)</hosts>
			<users>45.262 million; 44.625 million (metropolitan France) (2009)</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>475</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">14</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">27</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">98</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">83</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Calais, Dunkerque, Le Havre, Marseille, Nantes, Paris, Rouen</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army (Armee de Terre; includes Marines, Foreign Legion, Army Light Aviation), Navy (Marine Nationale, includes Naval Air, Maritime Gendarmerie (Coast Guard)), Air Force (Armee de l'Air (AdlA), includes Air Defense), National Gendarmerie (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>14563</male>
				<female>14238</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>12025</male>
				<female>11721</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>396050</male>
				<female>377839</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Madagascar claims the French territories of Bassas da India, Europa Island, Glorioso Islands, and Juan de Nova Island; Comoros claims Mayotte; Mauritius claims Tromelin Island; territorial dispute between Suriname and the French overseas department of French Guiana; France asserts a territorial claim in Antarctica (Adelie Land); France and Vanuatu claim Matthew and Hunter Islands, east of New Caledonia</disputes>
		<drugs>[object Object]</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>gm</code>
	<name>Germany</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>As Europe's largest economy and second most populous nation (after Russia), Germany is a key member of the continent's economic, political, and defense organizations. European power struggles immersed Germany in two devastating World Wars in the first half of the 20th century and left the country occupied by the victorious Allied powers of the US, UK, France, and the Soviet Union in 1945. With the advent of the Cold War, two German states were formed in 1949: the western Federal Republic of Germany (FRG) and the eastern German Democratic Republic (GDR). The democratic FRG embedded itself in key Western economic and security organizations, the EC, which became the EU, and NATO, while the Communist GDR was on the front line of the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact. The decline of the USSR and the end of the Cold War allowed for German unification in 1990. Since then, Germany has expended considerable funds to bring Eastern productivity and wages up to Western standards. In January 1999, Germany and 10 other EU countries introduced a common European exchange currency, the euro. In January 2011, Germany assumed a nonpermanent seat on the UN Security Council for the 2011-12 term.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location on North European Plain and along the entrance to the Baltic Sea</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Central Europe, bordering the Baltic Sea and the North Sea, between the Netherlands and Poland, south of Denmark</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">357022</total>
			<land unit="sq km">348672</land>
			<water unit="sq km">8350</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Montana</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">2389</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate and marine; cool, cloudy, wet winters and summers; occasional warm mountain (foehn) wind</climate>
		<terrain>lowlands in north, uplands in center, Bavarian Alps in south</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Zugspitze 2,963 m</high>
			<low>Neuendorf bei Wilster -3.54 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, lignite, natural gas, iron ore, copper, nickel, uranium, potash, salt, construction materials, timber, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">33.13</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.6</crops>
			<other unit="%">66.27</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>flooding</hazards>
		<issues>emissions from coal-burning utilities and industries contribute to air pollution; acid rain, resulting from sulfur dioxide emissions, is damaging forests; pollution in the Baltic Sea from raw sewage and industrial effluents from rivers in eastern Germany; hazardous waste disposal; government established a mechanism for ending the use of nuclear power over the next 15 years; government working to meet EU commitment to identify nature preservation areas in line with the EU's Flora, Fauna, and Habitat directive</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">4850</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">188</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">38.01</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">460</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>81471</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">8.3</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.92</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">0.54</migration>
			<growth unit=""></growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">13.3</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.1</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>44.9</total>
			<male>43.7</male>
			<female>46</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">74</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0</rate>
			<cities>BERLIN (capital) 3.438 million; Hamburg 1.786 million; Munich 1.349 million; Cologne 1.001 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.055</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.04</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.72</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.97</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.54</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.84</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.21</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">80.07</total>
			<male unit="years">77.82</male>
			<female unit="years">82.44</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.41">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>67000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>German(s)</noun>
			<adjective>German</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>German 91.5%, Turkish 2.4%, other 6.1% (made up largely of Greek, Italian, Polish, Russian, Serbo-Croatian, Spanish)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Protestant 34%, Roman Catholic 34%, Muslim 3.7%, unaffiliated or other 28.3%</religions>
		<languages>German</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.5</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Federal Republic of Germany</long>
			<short>Germany</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>federal republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Berlin</name>
			<coordinates>52° 31' N, 13° 24' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>16 states (Laender, singular - Land); Baden-Wurttemberg, Bayern (Bavaria), Berlin, Brandenburg, Bremen, Hamburg, Hessen (Hesse), Mecklenburg-Vorpommern (Mecklenburg-Western Pomerania), Niedersachsen (Lower Saxony), Nordrhein-Westfalen (North Rhine-Westphalia), Rheinland-Pfalz (Rhineland-Palatinate), Saarland, Sachsen (Saxony), Sachsen-Anhalt (Saxony-Anhalt), Schleswig-Holstein, Thueringen (Thuringia); note - Bayern, Sachsen, and Thueringen refer to themselves as free states (Freistaaten, singular - Freistaat)</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>18 January 1871 (German Empire unification); divided into four zones of occupation (UK, US, USSR, and France) in 1945 following World War II; Federal Republic of Germany (FRG or West Germany) proclaimed on 23 May 1949 and included the former UK, US, and French zones; German Democratic Republic (GDR or East Germany) proclaimed on 7 October 1949 and included the former USSR zone; West Germany and East Germany unified on 3 October 1990; all four powers formally relinquished rights on 15 March 1991; notable earlier dates: 10 August 843 (Eastern Francia established from the division of the Carolingian Empire); 2 February 962 (crowning of OTTO I, recognized as the first Holy Roman Emperor)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Unity Day, 3 October (1990)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Christian WULFF (since 30 June 2010)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Chancellor Angela MERKEL (since 22 November 2005)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet or Bundesminister (Federal Ministers) appointed by the president on the recommendation of the chancellor</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected for a five-year term (eligible for a second term) by a Federal Assembly, including all members of the Federal Diet and an equal number of delegates elected by the state parliaments; election last held on 30 June 2010 (next to be held by June 2015); chancellor elected by an absolute majority of the Federal Diet for a four-year term; Bundestag vote for Chancellor last held after 27 September 2009 (next to follow the legislative election to be held no later than 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>Christian WULFF elected president; received 625 votes of the Federal Assembly against 494 for GAUCK and 121 abstentions; Angela MERKEL reelected chancellor; vote by Federal Diet 323 to 285 with four abstentions</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral legislature consists of the Federal Council or Bundesrat (69 votes; state governments sit in the Council; each has three to six votes in proportion to population and is required to vote as a block) and the Federal Diet or Bundestag (622 seats; members elected by popular vote for a four-year term under a system of personalized proportional representation; a party must win 5% of the national vote or three direct mandates to gain proportional representation and caucus recognition)</description>
			<elections>Bundestag - last held on 27 September 2009 (next to be held no later than autumn 2013); note - there are no elections for the Bundesrat; composition is determined by the composition of the state-level governments; the composition of the Bundesrat has the potential to change any time one of the 16 states holds an election</elections>
			<election-results>Bundestag - percent of vote by party - CDU/CSU 33.8%, SPD 23%, FDP 14.6%, Left 11.9%, Greens 10.7%, other 6%; seats by party - CDU/CSU 239, SPD 146, FDP 93, Left 76, Greens 68</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Federal Constitutional Court or Bundesverfassungsgericht (half the judges are elected by the Bundestag and half by the Bundesrat); Federal Court of Justice; Federal Administrative Court</judicial>
		<parties>Alliance '90/Greens [Claudia ROTH and Cem OZDEMIR]; Christian Democratic Union or CDU [Angela MERKEL]; Christian Social Union or CSU [Horst SEEHOFER]; Free Democratic Party or FDP [Guido WESTERWELLE]; Left Party or Die Linke [Klaus ERNST and Gesine LOETZSCH]; Social Democratic Party or SPD [Sigmar GABRIEL]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, BIS, BSEC (observer), CBSS, CDB, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-20, G-5, G-7, G-8, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), SICA (observer), UN, UN Security Council (temporary), UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Klaus SCHARIOTH</chief>
			<chancery>4645 Reservoir Road NW, Washington, DC 20007</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 298-4000</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 298-4249</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Philip D. MURPHY</chief>
			<embassy>Pariser Platz 2, 14191 Berlin; note - new embassy opened 4 July 2008</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 120, Box 1000, APO AE 09265, Clayallee 170, 14195 Berlin</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[49] (030) 2385174</telephone>
			<FAX>[49] (030) 8305-1215</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal horizontal bands of black (top), red, and gold; these colors have played an important role in German history and can be traced back to the medieval banner of the Holy Roman Emperor - a black eagle with red claws and beak on a gold field</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Lied der Deutschen&quot; (Song of the Germans)</name>
			<by>August Heinrich HOFFMANN VON FALLERSLEBE/Franz Joseph HAYDN</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The German economy - the fifth largest economy in the world in PPP terms and Europe's largest - is a leading exporter of machinery, vehicles, chemicals, and household equipment and benefits from a highly skilled labor force. Like its western European neighbors, Germany faces significant demographic challenges to sustained long-term growth. Low fertility rates and declining net immigration are increasing pressure on the country's social welfare system and necessitate structural reforms. The modernization and integration of the eastern German economy - where unemployment can exceed 20% in some municipalities - continues to be a costly long-term process, with annual transfers from west to east amounting in 2008 alone to roughly $12 billion. Reforms launched by the government of Chancellor Gerhard SCHROEDER (1998-2005), deemed necessary to address chronically high unemployment and low average growth, contributed to strong growth in 2006 and 2007 and falling unemployment. These advances, as well as a government subsidized, reduced working hour scheme, help explain the relatively modest increase in unemployment during the 2008-09 recession - the deepest since World War II - and its decrease to 7.4%in 2010. GDP contracted 4.7% in 2009 but grew by 3.6% in 2010. In its annual projection for 2011, the Federal Government expects the upswing to continue, with GDP forecast to grow this year at a real rate of 2.3%. The recovery was attributable primarily to rebounding manufacturing orders and exports - increasingly outside the Euro Zone. Domestic demand, however, is becoming more significant driver of Germany's economic expansion. Stimulus and stabilization efforts initiated in 2008 and 2009 and tax cuts introduced in Chancellor Angela MERKEL's second term increased Germany's budget deficit to 3.5% in 2010. The Bundesbank expects the deficit to drop to about 2.5% in 2011, below the EU's 3% limit. A constitutional amendment approved in 2009 likewise limits the federal government to structural deficits of no more than 0.35% of GDP per annum as of 2016.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>3316000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">3.5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>43350000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit=""></unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">78.8</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.1</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">4.96</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">4288000000000.0005</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">5200000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>potatoes, wheat, barley, sugar beets, fruit, cabbages; cattle, pigs, poultry</agriculture-products>
		<industries>among the world's largest and most technologically advanced producers of iron, steel, coal, cement, chemicals, machinery, vehicles, machine tools, electronics, food and beverages, shipbuilding, textiles</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>593400000000</production>
			<consumption>547299999999.99994</consumption>
			<exports>61700000000</exports>
			<imports>41670000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">156800</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">2437000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">536600</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">2862000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">276000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">15290000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">96260000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">12640000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">94570000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">175600000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery, vehicles, chemicals, metals and manufactures, foodstuffs, textiles</commodities>
			<partners>France 10.2%, US 6.7%, Netherlands 6.7%, UK 6.6%, Italy 6.3%, Austria 6%, China 4.5%, Switzerland 4.4% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">1120000000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery, vehicles, chemicals, foodstuffs, textiles, metals</commodities>
			<partners>Netherlands 8.5%, China 8.2%, France 8.2%, US 5.9%, Italy 5.9%, UK 4.9%, Belgium 4.3%, Austria 4.3%, Switzerland 4.2% (2009 est.)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">4713000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>Germany has one of the world's most technologically advanced telecommunications systems; as a result of intensive capital expenditures since reunification, the formerly backward system of the eastern part of the country, dating back to World War II, has been modernized and integrated with that of the western part</assessment>
			<domestic>Germany is served by an extensive system of automatic telephone exchanges connected by modern networks of fiber-optic cable, coaxial cable, microwave radio relay, and a domestic satellite system; cellular telephone service is widely available, expanding rapidly, and includes roaming service to many foreign countries</domestic>
			<international>country code - 49; Germany's international service is excellent worldwide, consisting of extensive land and undersea cable facilities as well as earth stations in the Inmarsat, Intelsat, Eutelsat, and Intersputnik satellite systems (2001)</international>
			<land-lines>48700000</land-lines>
			<mobile>105000000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a mixture of publicly-operated and privately-owned TV and radio stations; national and regional public broadcasters compete with nearly 400 privately-owned national and regional TV stations; more than 90% of households have cable or satellite TV; hundreds of radio stations broadcasting including multiple national radio networks, regional radio networks, and a large number of local radio stations (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.de</tld>
			<hosts>21729000</hosts>
			<users>65125000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>549</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">53</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">59</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">70</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Bremen, Bremerhaven, Duisburg, Hamburg, Karlsruhe, Lubeck, Neuss-Dusseldorf, Rostock, Wilhemshaven</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Federal Armed Forces (Bundeswehr): Army (Heer), Navy (Deutsche Marine, includes naval air arm), Air Force (Luftwaffe), Joint Support Services (Streitkraeftbasis), Central Medical Service (Zentraler Sanitaetsdienst) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>18529</male>
				<female>17888</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>15027</male>
				<female>14510</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>405438</male>
				<female>384930</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs>source of precursor chemicals for South American cocaine processors; transshipment point for and consumer of Southwest Asian heroin, Latin American cocaine, and European-produced synthetic drugs; major financial center</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>gr</code>
	<name>Greece</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Greece achieved independence from the Ottoman Empire in 1829. During the second half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century, it gradually added neighboring islands and territories, most with Greek-speaking populations. In World War II, Greece was first invaded by Italy (1940) and subsequently occupied by Germany (1941-44); fighting endured in a protracted civil war between supporters of the king and other anti-Communists and Communist rebels. Following the latter's defeat in 1949, Greece joined NATO in 1952. In 1967, a group of military officers seized power, establishing a military dictatorship that suspended many political liberties and forced the king to flee the country. In 1974, democratic elections and a referendum created a parliamentary republic and abolished the monarchy. In 1981, Greece joined the EC (now the EU); it became the 12th member of the European Economic and Monetary Union in 2001. In 2010, the prospect of a Greek default on its euro-denominated debt created severe strains within the EMU and raised the question of whether a member country might voluntarily leave the common currency or be removed.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location dominating the Aegean Sea and southern approach to Turkish Straits; a peninsular country, possessing an archipelago of about 2,000 islands</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southern Europe, bordering the Aegean Sea, Ionian Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea, between Albania and Turkey</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">131957</total>
			<land unit="sq km">130647</land>
			<water unit="sq km">1310</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Alabama</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">13676</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; mild, wet winters; hot, dry summers</climate>
		<terrain>mostly mountains with ranges extending into the sea as peninsulas or chains of islands</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mount Olympus 2,917 m</high>
			<low>Mediterranean Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>lignite, petroleum, iron ore, bauxite, lead, zinc, nickel, magnesite, marble, salt, hydropower potential</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">20.45</arable>
			<crops unit="%">8.59</crops>
			<other unit="%">70.96</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution; water pollution</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">15500</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">72</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">8.7</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">782</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>10760</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">9.21</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.7</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">2.32</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.083</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">14.2</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.2</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>42.5</total>
			<male>41.4</male>
			<female>43.6</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">61</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</rate>
			<cities>ATHENS (capital) 3.252 million; Thessaloniki 834,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.064</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.78</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.49</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.48</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.92</total>
			<male unit="years">77.36</male>
			<female unit="years">82.65</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.38">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>8800</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 500 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Greek(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Greek</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>[object Object]</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Greek Orthodox (official) 98%, Muslim 1.3%, other 0.7%</religions>
		<languages>Greek (official) 99%, other (includes English and French) 1%</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">96</total>
			<male unit="%">97.8</male>
			<female unit="%">94.2</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">17</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Hellenic Republic</long>
			<short>Greece</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>parliamentary republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Athens</name>
			<coordinates>37° 59' N, 23° 44' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+2 (7 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>51 prefectures (nomoi, singular - nomos) and 1 autonomous region*; Achaia, Agion Oros* (Mount Athos), Aitolia kai Akarnania, Argolis, Arkadia, Arta, Attiki, Chalkidiki, Chania, Chios, Dodekanisos, Drama, Evros, Evrytania, Evvoia, Florina, Fokidos, Fthiotis, Grevena, Ileia, Imathia, Ioannina, Irakleion, Karditsa, Kastoria, Kavala, Kefallinia, Kerkyra, Kilkis, Korinthia, Kozani, Kyklades, Lakonia, Larisa, Lasithi, Lefkada, Lesvos, Magnisia, Messinia, Pella, Pieria, Preveza, Rethymnis, Rodopi, Samos, Serres, Thesprotia, Thessaloniki, Trikala, Voiotia, Xanthi, Zakynthos</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1829</independence>
		<national-holiday>Independence Day, 25 March (1821)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil legal system based on Roman law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal and compulsory</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Karolos PAPOULIAS (since 12 March 2005)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Georgios Andreas PAPANDREOU (since 6 October 2009)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the president on the recommendation of the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by parliament for a five-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 3 February 2010 (next to be held by February 2015); president appoints leader of the party securing plurality of vote in election to become prime minister and form a government</elections>
			<election-results>Karolos PAPOULIAS reelected president; number of parliamentary votes, 266 out of 300</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral Parliament or Vouli ton Ellinon (300 seats; members elected by direct popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 4 October 2009 (next to be held by 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - PASOK 43.9%, ND 33.5%, KKE 7.5%, LAOS 5.6%, SYRIZA 4.6%, other 4.9%; seats by party - PASOK 160, ND 91, KKE 21, LAOS 15, SYRIZA 13; note - seats by party as of 15 December 2010 - PASOK 156, ND 86, KKE 21 LAOS 15, SYRIZA 9, DISY 5, Democratic Left 4, independents 4 (DISY and Democratic Left entered parliament as members of ND and SYRIZA, respectively, and the independents entered parliament as members of PASOK); only parties surpassing a 3% threshold are entitled to parliamentary seats; parties need 10 seats to become formal parliamentary groups, but can retain that status if the party participated in the last election and received the minimum 3% threshold</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Civil and Criminal Court; all judges are appointed for life by the president after consultation with a judicial council; Supreme Administrative Court and Court of Auditors; Courts of Appeal; Courts of First Instance</judicial>
		<parties>Anticapitalist Left Cooperation for the Overthrow or ANTARSYA [Petros KONSTANTINOU]; Coalition of the Radical Left or SYRIZA [Alexis TSIPRAS]; Communist Party of Greece or KKE [Aleka PAPARIGA]; Democratic Left [Fotis KOUVELIS]; Democratic Alliance or DISY [Theodora BAKOGIANNI]; Ecologist Greens [Nikos CHRYSOGELOS]; Golden Dawn [Nikolaos MICHALOLIAKOS]; New Democracy or ND [Antonis SAMARAS]; Panhellenic Socialist Movement or PASOK [Georgios PAPANDREOU]; Popular Orthodox Rally or LAOS [Georgios KARATZAFERIS]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>Australia Group, BIS, BSEC, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MINURSO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OIF, OPCW, OSCE, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNMIS, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Vassilis KASKARELIS</chief>
			<chancery>2217 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 939-1300</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 939-1324</FAX>
			<consulates>Boston, Chicago, Los Angeles, New York, San Francisco, Tampa</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Daniel Bennett SMITH</chief>
			<embassy>91 Vasilisis Sophias Avenue, 10160 Athens</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 108, APO AE 09842-0108</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[30] (210) 721-2951</telephone>
			<FAX>[30] (210) 645-6282</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>nine equal horizontal stripes of blue alternating with white; a blue square bearing a white cross appears in the upper hoist-side corner; the cross symbolizes Greek Orthodoxy, the established religion of the country; there is no agreed upon meaning for the nine stripes or for the colors; the exact shade of blue has never been set by law and has varied from a light to a dark blue over time</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Ymnos eis tin Eleftherian&quot; (Hymn to Liberty)</name>
			<by>Dionysios SOLOMOS/Nikolaos MANTZAROS</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Greece has a capitalist economy with the public sector accounting for about 40% of GDP and with per capita GDP about two-thirds that of the leading euro-zone economies. Tourism provides 15% of GDP. Immigrants make up nearly one-fifth of the work force, mainly in agricultural and unskilled jobs. Greece is a major beneficiary of EU aid, equal to about 3.3% of annual GDP. The Greek economy grew by nearly 4.0% per year between 2003 and 2007, due partly to infrastructural spending related to the 2004 Athens Olympic Games, and in part to an increased availability of credit, which has sustained record levels of consumer spending. But the economy went into recession in 2009 as a result of the world financial crisis, tightening credit conditions, and Athens' failure to address a growing budget deficit, which was triggered by falling state revenues, and increased government expenditures. The economy contracted by 2% in 2009, and 4.8% in 2010. Greece violated the EU's Growth and Stability Pact budget deficit criterion of no more than 3% of GDP from 2001 to 2006, but finally met that criterion in 2007-08, before exceeding it again in 2009, with the deficit reaching 15.4% of GDP. Austerity measures reduced the deficit to 9.4% of GDP in 2010. Public debt, inflation, and unemployment are above the euro-zone average while per capita income is below; unemployment rose to 12% in 2010. Eroding public finances, a credibility gap stemming from inaccurate and misreported statistics, and consistent underperformance on following through with reforms prompted major credit rating agencies in late 2009 to downgrade Greece's international debt rating, and has led the country into a financial crisis. Under intense pressure by the EU and international market participants, the government has adopted a medium-term austerity program that includes cutting government spending, reducing the size of the public sector, decreasing tax evasion, reforming the health care and pension systems, and improving competitiveness through structural reforms to the labor and product markets. Athens, however, faces long-term challenges to push through unpopular reforms in the face of often vocal opposition from the country's powerful labor unions and the general public. Greek labor unions are striking over new austerity measures, but the strikes so far have had a limited impact on the government's will to adopt reforms. An uptick in widespread unrest, however, could challenge the government's ability to implement reforms and meet budget targets, and could also lead to rioting or violence. In April 2010 a leading credit agency assigned Greek debt its lowest possible credit rating; in May, the International Monetary Fund and Eurozone governments provided Greece emergency short- and medium-term loans worth $147 billion so that the country could make debt repayments to creditors. In exchange for the largest bailout ever assembled, the government announced combined spending cuts and tax increases totaling $40 billion over three years, on top of the tough austerity measures already taken. Greece, however, struggled to boost revenues and cut spending to meet 2010 targets set by the EU and the IMF, especially after Eurostat - the EU's statistical office - revised upward Greece's deficit and debt numbers for 2009 and 2010. Greece's lenders are calling on Athens to step up efforts in 2011 to increase tax collection, shore up public enterprises, and rein in health spending, and are planning to give Greece more time to repay its EU-IMF loan. Greece responded by introducing major structural reforms, but investors still question whether Greece can sustain fiscal efforts in the face of a bleak economic outlook and public discontent.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>305400000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit=""></real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>5050000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">12</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">144</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">4.5</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">8.59</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">335900000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">419900000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>wheat, corn, barley, sugar beets, olives, tomatoes, wine, tobacco, potatoes; beef, dairy products</agriculture-products>
		<industries>tourism, food and tobacco processing, textiles, chemicals, metal products; mining, petroleum</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>58790000000</production>
			<consumption>58280000000</consumption>
			<exports>1962000000</exports>
			<imports>7575000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">6779</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">414400</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">153000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">520900</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">10000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">9000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">3528000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">3556000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">991100000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>food and beverages, manufactured goods, petroleum products, chemicals, textiles</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 11.11%, Italy 11.05%, Cyprus 7.28%, Bulgaria 6.74%, US 4.95%, UK 4.4%, Turkey 4.23% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">44900000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery, transport equipment, fuels, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 13.73%, Italy 12.71%, China 7.08%, France 6.1%, Netherlands 6.02%, South Korea 5.68%, Belgium 4.34%, Spain 4.08% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">532900000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>adequate, modern networks reach all areas; good mobile telephone and international service</assessment>
			<domestic>microwave radio relay trunk system; extensive open-wire connections; submarine cable to offshore islands</domestic>
			<international>country code - 30; landing point for the SEA-ME-WE-3 optical telecommunications submarine cable that provides links to Europe, Middle East, and Asia; a number of smaller submarine cables provide connectivity to various parts of Europe, the Middle East, and Cyprus; tropospheric scatter; satellite earth stations - 4 (2 Intelsat - 1 Atlantic Ocean and 1 Indian Ocean, 1 Eutelsat, and 1 Inmarsat - Indian Ocean region)</international>
			<land-lines>5930000</land-lines>
			<mobile>13295000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>broadcast media dominated by the private sector; roughly 150 private TV channels, about a dozen of the private channels broadcast at the national or regional level; 3 publicly-owned terrestrial TV channels with national coverage, 1 publicly-owned satellite channel, and 3 stations designed for digital terrestrial transmissions; multi-channel satellite and cable TV services obtainable; upwards of 1,500 radio stations broadcasting, nearly all of them privately-owned; state-run broadcaster has 7 national stations, 2 international stations, and 19 regional stations (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.gr</tld>
			<hosts>2574000</hosts>
			<users>4971000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>81</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">6</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">14</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">20</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Agioi Theodoroi, Aspropyrgos, Pachi, Piraeus, Thessaloniki</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Hellenic Army (Ellinikos Stratos, ES), Hellenic Navy (Ellinikos Polemiko Navtiko, EPN), Hellenic Air Force (Elliniki Polemiki Aeroporia, EPA) (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2485</male>
				<female>2469</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>2032</male>
				<female>2016</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>52754</male>
				<female>49485</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Greece and Turkey continue discussions to resolve their complex maritime, air, territorial, and boundary disputes in the Aegean Sea; Cyprus question with Turkey; Greece rejects the use of the name Macedonia or Republic of Macedonia; the mass migration of unemployed Albanians still remains a problem for developed countries, chiefly Greece and Italy</disputes>
		<drugs>a gateway to Europe for traffickers smuggling cannabis and heroin from the Middle East and Southwest Asia to the West and precursor chemicals to the East; some South American cocaine transits or is consumed in Greece; money laundering related to drug trafficking and organized crime</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>it</code>
	<name>Italy</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Italy became a nation-state in 1861 when the regional states of the peninsula, along with Sardinia and Sicily, were united under King Victor EMMANUEL II. An era of parliamentary government came to a close in the early 1920s when Benito MUSSOLINI established a Fascist dictatorship. His alliance with Nazi Germany led to Italy's defeat in World War II. A democratic republic replaced the monarchy in 1946 and economic revival followed. Italy was a charter member of NATO and the European Economic Community (EEC). It has been at the forefront of European economic and political unification, joining the Economic and Monetary Union in 1999. Persistent problems include illegal immigration, organized crime, corruption, high unemployment, sluggish economic growth, and the low incomes and technical standards of southern Italy compared with the prosperous north.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location dominating central Mediterranean as well as southern sea and air approaches to Western Europe</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southern Europe, a peninsula extending into the central Mediterranean Sea, northeast of Tunisia</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">301340</total>
			<land unit="sq km">294140</land>
			<water unit="sq km">7200</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than Arizona</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">7600</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>predominantly Mediterranean; Alpine in far north; hot, dry in south</climate>
		<terrain>mostly rugged and mountainous; some plains, coastal lowlands</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mont Blanc (Monte Bianco) de Courmayeur 4,748 m (a secondary peak of Mont Blanc)</high>
			<low>Mediterranean Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, mercury, zinc, potash, marble, barite, asbestos, pumice, fluorspar, feldspar, pyrite (sulfur), natural gas and crude oil reserves, fish, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">26.41</arable>
			<crops unit="%">9.09</crops>
			<other unit="%">64.5</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>air pollution from industrial emissions such as sulfur dioxide; coastal and inland rivers polluted from industrial and agricultural effluents; acid rain damaging lakes; inadequate industrial waste treatment and disposal facilities</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">39500</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">175</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">41.98</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">723</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>61016</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">9.18</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">9.84</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">4.86</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.42</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">13.8</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">65.9</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>43.5</total>
			<male>42.4</male>
			<female>44.7</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">68</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.5</rate>
			<cities>ROME (capital) 3.357 million; Milan 2.962 million; Naples 2.27 million; Turin 1.662 million; Palermo 872,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.059</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.72</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.38</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.59</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.16</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.77</total>
			<male unit="years">79.16</male>
			<female unit="years">84.53</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.39">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>140000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access></sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Italian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Italian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Italian (includes small clusters of German-, French-, and Slovene-Italians in the north and Albanian-Italians and Greek-Italians in the south)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 90% (approximately; about one-third practicing), other 10% (includes mature Protestant and Jewish communities and a growing Muslim immigrant community)</religions>
		<languages>Italian (official), German (parts of Trentino-Alto Adige region are predominantly German speaking), French (small French-speaking minority in Valle d'Aosta region), Slovene (Slovene-speaking minority in the Trieste-Gorizia area)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">98.4</total>
			<male unit="%">98.8</male>
			<female unit="%">98</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.3</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Italian Republic</long>
			<short>Italy</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>republic</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Rome</name>
			<coordinates>41° 54' N, 12° 29' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>17 March 1861 (Kingdom of Italy proclaimed; Italy was not finally unified until 1870)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Republic Day, 2 June (1946)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system; judicial review under certain conditions in Constitutional Court</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal (except in senatorial elections, where minimum age is 25)</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>President Giorgio NAPOLITANO (since 15 May 2006)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Silvio BERLUSCONI (since 8 May 2008); note - in Italy the prime minister is referred to as the president of the Council of Ministers</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers proposed by the prime minister and nominated by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>president elected by an electoral college consisting of both houses of parliament and 58 regional representatives for a seven-year term (no term limits); election last held on 10 May 2006 (next to be held in May 2013); prime minister appointed by the president and confirmed by parliament</elections>
			<election-results>Giorgio NAPOLITANO elected president on the fourth round of voting; electoral college vote - 543</election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament or Parlamento consists of the Senate or Senato della Repubblica (315 seats; members elected by proportional vote with the winning coalition in each region receiving 55% of seats from that region; members to serve five-year terms; and up to 5 senators for life appointed by the president of the Republic) and the Chamber of Deputies or Camera dei Deputati (630 seats; members elected by popular vote with the winning national coalition receiving 54% of chamber seats; members to serve five-year terms); note - it has not been clarified if each president has the power to designate up to five senators or if five is the number of senators for life who might sit in the Senate</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 13-14 April 2008 (next to be held in April 2013); Chamber of Deputies - last held on 13-14 April 2008 (next to be held in April 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - S. BERLUSCONI coalition 174 (PdL 147, LN 25, MpA 2), W. VELTRONI coalition 132 (PD 118, IdV 3), UdC 3, other 6; Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - S. BERLUSCONI coalition 344 (PdL 276, LN 60, MpA 8), W. VELTRONI coalition 246 (PD 217, IdV 29), UdC 36, other 4</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Constitutional Court or Corte Costituzionale (composed of 15 judges: one-third appointed by the president, one-third elected by parliament, one-third elected by the ordinary and administrative Supreme Courts)</judicial>
		<parties>[object Object]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Australia Group, BIS, BSEC (observer), CBSS (observer), CD, CDB, CE, CEI, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-20, G-7, G-8, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAIA (observer), MIGA, MINURSO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PIF (partner), Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), SICA (observer), UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, Union Latina, UNMOGIP, UNRWA, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Giulio TERZI di Sant' Agata</chief>
			<chancery>3000 Whitehaven Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 612-4400</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 518-2151</FAX>
			<consulates>Boston, Chicago, Houston, Miami, New York, Los Angeles, Philadelphia, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador David THORNE</chief>
			<embassy>Via Vittorio Veneto 121, 00187-Rome</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 59, Box 100, APO AE 09624</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[39] (06) 46741</telephone>
			<FAX>[39] (06) 488-2672, 4674-2356</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Il Canto degli Italiani&quot; (The Song of the Italians)</name>
			<by>Goffredo MAMELI/Michele NOVARO</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Italy has a diversified industrial economy, which is divided into a developed industrial north, dominated by private companies, and a less-developed, welfare-dependent, agricultural south, with high unemployment. The Italian economy is driven in large part by the manufacture of high-quality consumer goods produced by small and medium-sized enterprises, many of them family owned. Italy also has a sizable underground economy, which by some estimates accounts for as much as 15% of GDP. These activities are most common within the agriculture, construction, and service sectors. Italy has moved slowly on implementing needed structural reforms, such as reducing graft, overhauling costly entitlement programs, and increasing employment opportunities for young workers, particularly women. The international financial crisis worsened conditions in Italy's labor market, with unemployment rising from 6.2% in 2007 to 8.4% in 2010, but in the longer-term Italy's low fertility rate and quota-driven immigration policies will increasingly strain its economy. A rise in exports and investment driven by the global economic recovery nevertheless helped the economy grow by about 1% in 2010 following a 5% contraction in 2009. The Italian government has struggled to limit government spending, but Italy's exceedingly high public debt remains above 115% of GDP, and its fiscal deficit - just 1.5% of GDP in 2007 - exceeded 5% in 2009 and 2010, as the costs of servicing the country's debt rose.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>2055000000000.0002</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.3</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>25050000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">8.4</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">118.1</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.4</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">10.26</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">1884000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">3274000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>fruits, vegetables, grapes, potatoes, sugar beets, soybeans, grain, olives; beef, dairy products; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>tourism, machinery, iron and steel, chemicals, food processing, textiles, motor vehicles, clothing, footwear, ceramics</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>289700000000</production>
			<consumption>315000000000</consumption>
			<exports>3431000000</exports>
			<imports>43000000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">146500</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">1537000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">586900</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">1911000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">423700000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">8119000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">78120000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">124000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">69240000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">69830000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>engineering products, textiles and clothing, production machinery, motor vehicles, transport equipment, chemicals; food, beverages and tobacco; minerals, and nonferrous metals</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 12.6%, France 11.57%, US 5.92%, Spain 5.69%, UK 5.13%, Switzerland 4.69% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">459700000000</total>
			<commodities>engineering products, chemicals, transport equipment, energy products, minerals and nonferrous metals, textiles and clothing; food, beverages, and tobacco</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 16.68%, France 8.82%, China 6.53%, Netherlands 5.63%, Spain 4.3%, Russia 4.12%, Belgium 4.08% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">2223000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>modern, well developed, fast; fully automated telephone, telex, and data services</assessment>
			<domestic>high-capacity cable and microwave radio relay trunks</domestic>
			<international>country code - 39; a series of submarine cables provide links to Asia, Middle East, Europe, North Africa, and US; satellite earth stations - 3 Intelsat (with a total of 5 antennas - 3 for Atlantic Ocean and 2 for Indian Ocean), 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic Ocean region), and NA Eutelsat</international>
			<land-lines>21300000</land-lines>
			<mobile>90613000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>two Italian media giants - the publicly-owned Radiotelevisione Italiana (RAI) with 3 national terrestrial stations and privately-owned Mediaset with 3 national terrestrial stations - dominate; additional broadcasts by a large number of private stations and Sky Italia - a satellite TV network; RAI operates 3 AM/FM nationwide radio stations; some 1,300 commercial radio stations (2007)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.it</tld>
			<hosts>23160000</hosts>
			<users>29235000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>132</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">30</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">31</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Augusta, Cagliari, Genoa, Livorno, Santa Panagia (Melilli), Taranto, Trieste, Venice</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Italian Armed Forces: Army (Esercito Italiano, EI), Navy (Marina Militare Italiana, MMI), Italian Air Force (Aeronautica Militare Italiana, AMI), Carabinieri Corps (Arma dei Carabinieri, CC) (2011)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>13865</male>
				<female>14003</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>11247</male>
				<female>11348</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>288188</male>
				<female>281671</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Italy's long coastline and developed economy entices tens of thousands of illegal immigrants from southeastern Europe and northern Africa</disputes>
		<drugs>important gateway for and consumer of Latin American cocaine and Southwest Asian heroin entering the European market; money laundering by organized crime and from smuggling</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>nl</code>
	<name>Netherlands</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>The Dutch United Provinces declared their independence from Spain in 1579; during the 17th century, they became a leading seafaring and commercial power, with settlements and colonies around the world. After a 20-year French occupation, a Kingdom of the Netherlands was formed in 1815. In 1830 Belgium seceded and formed a separate kingdom. The Netherlands remained neutral in World War I, but suffered invasion and occupation by Germany in World War II. A modern, industrialized nation, the Netherlands is also a large exporter of agricultural products. The country was a founding member of NATO and the EEC (now the EU), and participated in the introduction of the euro in 1999. In October 2010, the former Netherlands Antilles was dissolved and the three smallest islands - Bonaire, Sint Eustatius, and Saba - became special municipalities in the Netherlands administrative structure. The larger islands of Sint Maarten and Curacao joined the Netherlands and Aruba as constituent countries forming the Kingdom of the Netherlands.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>located at mouths of three major European rivers (Rhine, Maas or Meuse, and Schelde)</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western Europe, bordering the North Sea, between Belgium and Germany</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">41543</total>
			<land unit="sq km">33893</land>
			<water unit="sq km">7650</water>
			<comparison>slightly less than twice the size of New Jersey</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">451</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; marine; cool summers and mild winters</climate>
		<terrain>mostly coastal lowland and reclaimed land (polders); some hills in southeast</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Mount Scenery 862 m (on the island of Saba in the Caribbean, now considered an integral part of the Netherlands following the dissolution of the Netherlands Antilles)</high>
			<low>Zuidplaspolder -7 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>natural gas, petroleum, peat, limestone, salt, sand and gravel, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">21.96</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.77</crops>
			<other unit="%">77.27</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>flooding</hazards>
		<issues>water pollution in the form of heavy metals, organic compounds, and nutrients such as nitrates and phosphates; air pollution from vehicles and refining activities; acid rain</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">4600</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">89.7</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">8.86</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">544</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>16847</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.23</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">8.85</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">2.33</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.371</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">17</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.4</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>41.1</total>
			<male>40.3</male>
			<female>41.9</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">83</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.8</rate>
			<cities>AMSTERDAM (capital) 1.044 million; Rotterdam 1.008 million; The Hague (seat of government) 629,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.052</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.76</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.98</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.59</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.08</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.07</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">79.68</total>
			<male unit="years">77.06</male>
			<female unit="years">82.44</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.66">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>22000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Dutchman(men), Dutchwoman(women)</noun>
			<adjective>Dutch</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Dutch 80.7%, EU 5%, Indonesian 2.4%, Turkish 2.2%, Surinamese 2%, Moroccan 2%, Caribbean 0.8%, other 4.8% (2008 est.)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 30%, Dutch Reformed 11%, Calvinist 6%, other Protestant 3%, Muslim 5.8%, other 2.2%, none 42% (2006)</religions>
		<languages>Dutch (official), Frisian (official)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">17</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.3</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of the Netherlands</long>
			<short>Netherlands</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Amsterdam</name>
			<coordinates>52° 23' N, 4° 54' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>12 provinces (provincies, singular - provincie); Drenthe, Flevoland, Fryslan (Friesland), Gelderland, Groningen, Limburg, Noord-Brabant (North Brabant), Noord-Holland (North Holland), Overijssel, Utrecht, Zeeland (Zealand), Zuid-Holland (South Holland)</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>23 January 1579 (the northern provinces of the Low Countries conclude the Union of Utrecht breaking with Spain; on 26 July 1581 they formally declared their independence with an Act of Abjuration; however, it was not until 30 January 1648 and the Peace of Westphalia that Spain recognized this independence)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Queen's Day (Birthday of deceased Queen-Mother JULIANA and accession to the throne of her oldest daughter BEATRIX), 30 April (1909 and 1980)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system based on the French system; constitution does not permit judicial review of acts of the States General</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>Queen BEATRIX (since 30 April 1980); Heir Apparent WILLEM-ALEXANDER (born 27 April 1967), son of the monarch</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Mark RUTTE (since 14 October 2010); Deputy Prime Minister Maxime VERHAGEN (since 14 October 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers appointed by the monarch</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following Second Chamber elections, the leader of the majority party or leader of a majority coalition usually appointed prime minister by the monarch; deputy prime ministers appointed by the monarch</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral States General or Staten Generaal consists of the First Chamber or Eerste Kamer (75 seats; members indirectly elected by the country's 12 provincial councils to serve four-year terms) and the Second Chamber or Tweede Kamer (150 seats; members elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>First Chamber - last held on 29 May 2007 (next to be held in May 2011); Second Chamber - last held on 9 June 2010 (next to be held by May 2015)</elections>
			<election-results>First Chamber - percent of vote by party - NA%; seats by party - CDA 21, PvdA 14, VVD 14, Socialist Party 11, Christian Union 4, Green Left Party 4, D66 2, other 5; Second Chamber - percent of vote by party - VVD 20.5%, PvdA 19.6%, PVV, 15.4%, CDA 13.6%, SP 9.8%, D66 6.9%, GL 6.7%, CU 3.2, other 4.3%; seats by party - VVD 31, PvdA 30, PVV 24, CDA 21, SP 15, D66 10, GL 10, CU 5, other 4</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Hoge Raad (justices are nominated for life by the monarch)</judicial>
		<parties>Christian Democratic Appeal or CDA [Maxime VERHAGEN]; Christian Union or CU [Andre ROUVOET]; Democrats 66 or D66 [Alexander PECHTOLD]; Green Left or GL [Jolande SAP]; Labor Party or PvdA [Job COHEN]; Party for Freedom or PVV [Geert WILDERS]; Party for the Animals or PvdD [Marianne THIEME]; People's Party for Freedom and Democracy or VVD [Mark RUTTE] (Liberal); Reformed Political Party of SGP [Kees VAN DER STAAIJ]; Socialist Party of SP [Emile ROEMER]; plus a few minor parties</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, Benelux, BIS, CBSS (observer), CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Regina &quot;Renee&quot; JONES-BOS</chief>
			<chancery>4200 Linnean Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 244-5300, [1] 877-388-2443</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 362-3430</FAX>
			<consulates>Chicago, Los Angeles, Miami, New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Fay HARTOG LEVIN</chief>
			<embassy>Lange Voorhout 102, 2514 EJ, The Hague</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 71, Box 1000, APO AE 09715</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[31] (70) 310-2209</telephone>
			<FAX>[31] (70) 361-4688</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>three equal horizontal bands of red (top), white, and blue; similar to the flag of Luxembourg, which uses a lighter blue and is longer; the colors were those of WILLIAM I, Prince of Orange, who led the Dutch Revolt against Spanish sovereignty in the latter half of the 16th century; originally the upper band was orange, but because it tended to fade to red over time, the red shade was eventually made the permanent color; the banner is perhaps the oldest tricolor in continuous use</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Het Wilhelmus&quot; (The William)</name>
			<by>Philips VAN MARNIX van Sint Aldegonde (presumed)/unknown</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The Netherlands economy is noted for stable industrial relations, moderate unemployment and inflation, a sizable current account surplus, and an important role as a European transportation hub. Industrial activity is predominantly in food processing, chemicals, petroleum refining, and electrical machinery. A highly mechanized agricultural sector employs only 2% of the labor force but provides large surpluses for the food-processing industry and for exports. The Netherlands, along with 11 of its EU partners, began circulating the euro currency on 1 January 2002. The country has been one of the leading European nations for attracting foreign direct investment and is one of the four largest investors in the US. After 26 years of uninterrupted economic growth, the Netherlands' economy - which is highly open and dependent on foreign trade and financial services - was hard-hit by global economic crisis. Dutch GDP contracted 3.9% in 2009, while exports declined nearly 25% due to a sharp contraction in world demand. The Dutch financial sector has also suffered, due in part to the high exposure of some Dutch banks to U.S. mortgage-backed securities. In response to turmoil in financial markets, the government nationalized two banks and injected billions of dollars into a third, to prevent further systemic risk. The government also sought to boost the domestic economy by accelerating infrastructure programs, offering corporate tax breaks for employers to retain workers, and expanding export credit facilities. The stimulus programs and bank bailouts, however, resulted in a government budget deficit of nearly 4.6% of GDP in 2009 and 5.6% in 2010 that contrasts sharply with a surplus of 0.7% of GDP in 2008. With unemployment weighing on private-sector consumption, the government of Prime Minister Mark RUTTE is likely to come under increased pressure to keep the budget deficit in check while promoting economic recovery.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>783300000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.7</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>7860000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">5.5</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">64.6</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.1</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">10.01</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">1124000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">2083000000000.0002</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grains, potatoes, sugar beets, fruits, vegetables; livestock</agriculture-products>
		<industries>agroindustries, metal and engineering products, electrical machinery and equipment, chemicals, petroleum, construction, microelectronics, fishing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>108200000000</production>
			<consumption>124100000000</consumption>
			<exports>10560000000</exports>
			<imports>15450000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">57190</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">922800</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">1660000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">2426000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">100000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">79580000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">48600000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">55590000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">24600000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">1416000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, chemicals, fuels; foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 25.54%, Belgium 12.49%, France 9.27%, UK 8.17%, Italy 5.07%, US 3.97% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">408400000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and transport equipment, chemicals, fuels, foodstuffs, clothing</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 17.16%, China 11.58%, Belgium 8.68%, US 7.77%, UK 5.72%, Russia 4.47%, France 4.4% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD"></external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>highly developed and well maintained</assessment>
			<domestic>extensive fixed-line fiber-optic network; large cellular telephone system with 5 major operators utilizing the third generation of the Global System for Mobile Communications (GSM) technology; one in five households now use Voice over the Internet Protocol (VoIP) services</domestic>
			<international>country code - 31; submarine cables provide links to the US and Europe; satellite earth stations - 5 (3 Intelsat - 1 Indian Ocean and 2 Atlantic Ocean, 1 Eutelsat, and 1 Inmarsat (2007)</international>
			<land-lines>7320000</land-lines>
			<mobile>21182000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>more than 90% of households are connected to cable or satellite TV systems that provide a wide range of domestic and foreign channels; public service broadcast system includes multiple broadcasters, 3 with a national reach and the remainder operating in regional and local markets; 2 major nationwide commercial television companies, each with 3 or more stations, and a large number of commercial TV stations in regional and local markets; nearly 600 radio stations operating with a mix of public and private stations providing national or regional coverage (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.nl</tld>
			<hosts>12607000</hosts>
			<users>14872000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>27</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">2</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">5</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Amsterdam, IJmuiden, Moerdijk, Rotterdam, Terneuzen, Vlissingen</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Royal Netherlands Army, Royal Netherlands Navy (includes Naval Air Service and Marine Corps), Royal Netherlands Air Force (Koninklijke Luchtmacht, KLu), Royal Military Police (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>3911</male>
				<female>3817</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>3201</male>
				<female>3122</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>103462</male>
				<female>98383</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs>major European producer of synthetic drugs, including ecstasy, and cannabis cultivator; important gateway for cocaine, heroin, and hashish entering Europe; major source of US-bound ecstasy; large financial sector vulnerable to money laundering; significant consumer of ecstasy</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>no</code>
	<name>Norway</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Two centuries of Viking raids into Europe tapered off following the adoption of Christianity by King Olav TRYGGVASON in 994. Conversion of the Norwegian kingdom occurred over the next several decades. In 1397, Norway was absorbed into a union with Denmark that lasted more than four centuries. In 1814, Norwegians resisted the cession of their country to Sweden and adopted a new constitution. Sweden then invaded Norway but agreed to let Norway keep its constitution in return for accepting the union under a Swedish king. Rising nationalism throughout the 19th century led to a 1905 referendum granting Norway independence. Although Norway remained neutral in World War I, it suffered heavy losses to its shipping. Norway proclaimed its neutrality at the outset of World War II, but was nonetheless occupied for five years by Nazi Germany (1940-45). In 1949, neutrality was abandoned and Norway became a member of NATO. Discovery of oil and gas in adjacent waters in the late 1960s boosted Norway's economic fortunes. In referenda held in 1972 and 1994, Norway rejected joining the EU. Key domestic issues include immigration and integration of ethnic minorities, maintaining the country's extensive social safety net with an aging population, and preserving economic competitiveness.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>about two-thirds mountains; some 50,000 islands off its much-indented coastline; strategic location adjacent to sea lanes and air routes in North Atlantic; one of the most rugged and longest coastlines in the world</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Europe, bordering the North Sea and the North Atlantic Ocean, west of Sweden</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">323802</total>
			<land unit="sq km">304282</land>
			<water unit="sq km">19520</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than New Mexico</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">25148</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">10</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf>[object Object]</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate along coast, modified by North Atlantic Current; colder interior with increased precipitation and colder summers; rainy year-round on west coast</climate>
		<terrain>glaciated; mostly high plateaus and rugged mountains broken by fertile valleys; small, scattered plains; coastline deeply indented by fjords; arctic tundra in north</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Galdhopiggen 2,469 m</high>
			<low>Norwegian Sea 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>petroleum, natural gas, iron ore, copper, lead, zinc, titanium, pyrites, nickel, fish, timber, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">2.7</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0</crops>
			<other unit="%">97.3</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>water pollution; acid rain damaging forests and adversely affecting lakes, threatening fish stocks; air pollution from vehicle emissions</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1180</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">381.4</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">2.4</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">519</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>4691</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.84</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">9.24</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">1.7</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.329</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">18</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>40</total>
			<male>39.1</male>
			<female>40.8</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">79</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1.2</rate>
			<cities>OSLO (capital) 875,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.054</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.04</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.76</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.98</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.52</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.85</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.17</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">80.2</total>
			<male unit="years">77.53</male>
			<female unit="years">83.02</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.77">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>4000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Norwegian(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Norwegian</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>Norwegian 94.4% (includes Sami, about 60,000), other European 3.6%, other 2% (2007 estimate)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Church of Norway 85.7%, Pentecostal 1%, Roman Catholic 1%, other Christian 2.4%, Muslim 1.8%, other 8.1% (2004)</religions>
		<languages>[object Object]</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">100</total>
			<male unit="%">100</male>
			<female unit="%">100</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">17</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">6.8</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Norway</long>
			<short>Norway</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Oslo</name>
			<coordinates>59° 55' N, 10° 45' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>19 counties (fylker, singular - fylke); Akershus, Aust-Agder, Buskerud, Finnmark, Hedmark, Hordaland, More og Romsdal, Nordland, Nord-Trondelag, Oppland, Oslo, Ostfold, Rogaland, Sogn og Fjordane, Sor-Trondelag, Telemark, Troms, Vest-Agder, Vestfold</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>7 June 1905 (Norway declared the union with Sweden dissolved); 26 October 1905 (Sweden agreed to the repeal of the union)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Constitution Day, 17 May (1814)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>mixed legal system of civil, common, and customary law; Supreme Court can advise on legislative acts</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King HARALD V (since 17 January 1991); Heir Apparent Crown Prince HAAKON MAGNUS, son of the monarch (born 20 July 1973)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Jens STOLTENBERG (since 17 October 2005)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>State Council appointed by the monarch with the approval of parliament</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following parliamentary elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually appointed prime minister by the monarch with the approval of the parliament</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>modified unicameral Parliament or Storting (169 seats; members elected by popular vote by proportional representation to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 14 September 2009 (next to be held in September 2013)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - DNA 35.4%, FrP 22.9%, H 17.2%, SV 6.2%, Sp 6.2%, KrF 5.5%, V 3.9%, other 2.7%; seats by party - DNA 64, FrP 41, H 30, SV 11, Sp 11, KrF 10, V 2</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Hoyesterett (justices appointed by the monarch)</judicial>
		<parties>Center Party (Senterpartiet or Sp) [Liv Signe NAVARSETE]; Christian People's Party (Kristelig Folkeparti or KrF) [Dagfinn HOYBRATEN]; Conservative Party (Hoyre or H) [Erna SOLBERG]; Labor Party (Det norske Arbeiderpartiet or DNA) [Jens STOLTENBERG]; Liberal Party (Venstre or V) [Trine SKEI-GRANDE]; Progress Party (Framstegspartiet or FrP) [Siv JENSEN]; Socialist Left Party (Sosialistisk Venstreparti or SV) [Kristin HALVORSEN]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council, Australia Group, BIS, CBSS, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EFTA, ESA, FAO, FATF, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NC, NEA, NIB, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNITAR, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Wegger C. STROMMEN</chief>
			<chancery>2720 34th Street NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 333-6000</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 337-0870</FAX>
			<consulates>Houston, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Barry B. WHITE</chief>
			<embassy>Henrik Ibsens gate 48, 0244 Oslo; note - the embassy will move to Huseby in the near future</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 69, Box 1000, APO AE 09707</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[47] 22 44 85 50</telephone>
			<FAX>[47] 22 44 33 63, 22 56 27 51</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>red with a blue cross outlined in white that extends to the edges of the flag; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side in the style of the Dannebrog (Danish flag); the colors recall Norway's past political unions with Denmark (red and white) and Sweden (blue)</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Ja, vi elsker dette landet&quot; (Yes, We Love This Country)</name>
			<by>Bjornstjerne BJORNSON/Rikard NORDRAAK</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The Norwegian economy is a prosperous bastion of welfare capitalism, featuring a combination of free market activity and government intervention. The government controls key areas, such as the vital petroleum sector, through large-scale state-majority-owned enterprises. The country is richly endowed with natural resources - petroleum, hydropower, fish, forests, and minerals - and is highly dependent on the petroleum sector, which accounts for nearly half of exports and over 30% of state revenue. Norway is the world's second-largest gas exporter; its position as an oil exporter has slipped to ninth-largest as production has begun to decline. Norway opted to stay out of the EU during a referendum in November 1994; nonetheless, as a member of the European Economic Area, it contributes sizably to the EU budget. In anticipation of eventual declines in oil and gas production, Norway saves state revenue from the petroleum sector in the world's second largest sovereign wealth fund, valued at over $500 billion in 2010. After solid GDP growth in 2004-07, the economy slowed in 2008, and contracted in 2009, before returning to positive growth in 2010.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>414500000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">0.4</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>2590000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">3.6</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">47.7</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">2.4</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">4</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">4.28</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">122200000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">256300000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">414500000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>barley, wheat, potatoes; pork, beef, veal, milk; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>petroleum and gas, food processing, shipbuilding, pulp and paper products, metals, chemicals, timber, mining, textiles, fishing</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>142700000000</production>
			<consumption>128800000000.00002</consumption>
			<exports>17290000000</exports>
			<imports>3414000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">2350000</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">204100</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">2150000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">107500</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">6680000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">103500000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">4620000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">98850000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">0</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">2313000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>petroleum and petroleum products, machinery and equipment, metals, chemicals, ships, fish</commodities>
			<partners>UK 24.28%, Germany 13.4%, Netherlands 10.87%, France 8.55%, Sweden 5.76%, US 4.82% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">74020000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, chemicals, metals, foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Sweden 13.86%, Germany 12.89%, China 7.8%, Denmark 6.78%, US 6.16%, UK 6.01% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD"></external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Norwegian kroner (NOK) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>modern in all respects; one of the most advanced telecommunications networks in Europe</assessment>
			<domestic>Norway has a domestic satellite system; the prevalence of rural areas encourages the wide use of mobile-cellular systems</domestic>
			<international>country code - 47; 2 buried coaxial cable systems; submarine cables provide links to other Nordic countries and Europe; satellite earth stations - NA Eutelsat, NA Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean), and 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic and Indian Ocean regions); note - Norway shares the Inmarsat earth station with the other Nordic countries (Denmark, Finland, Iceland, and Sweden) (1999)</international>
			<land-lines>1900000</land-lines>
			<mobile>5336000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>state-owned public radio-TV broadcaster operates 3 nationwide television stations, 3 nationwide radio stations, and 16 regional radio stations; roughly a dozen privately-owned television stations broadcast nationally and roughly another 25 local TV stations are available; nearly 75% of households have access to multi-channel cable or satellite TV systems; 2 privately-owned radio stations broadcast nationwide and another 240 stations operate locally (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.no</tld>
			<hosts>3352000</hosts>
			<users>4431000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>98</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">1</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">12</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">11</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Bergen, Haugesund, Maaloy, Mongstad, Narvik, Sture</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Norwegian Army (Haeren), Royal Norwegian Navy (Kongelige Norske Sjoeforsvaret, RNoN; includes Coastal Rangers and Coast Guard (Kystvakt)), Royal Norwegian Air Force (Kongelige Norske Luftforsvaret, RNoAF), Home Guard (Heimevernet, HV) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>1079</male>
				<female>1051</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>888761</male>
				<female>865697</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>32290</male>
				<female>30777</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>Norway asserts a territorial claim in Antarctica (Queen Maud Land and its continental shelf); Denmark (Greenland) and Norway have made submissions to the Commission on the Limits of the Continental shelf (CLCS) and Russia is collecting additional data to augment its 2001 CLCS submission; Norway and Russia signed a comprehensive maritime boundary agreement in 2010</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>sp</code>
	<name>Spain</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>Spain's powerful world empire of the 16th and 17th centuries ultimately yielded command of the seas to England. Subsequent failure to embrace the mercantile and industrial revolutions caused the country to fall behind Britain, France, and Germany in economic and political power. Spain remained neutral in World Wars I and II but suffered through a devastating civil war (1936-39). A peaceful transition to democracy following the death of dictator Francisco FRANCO in 1975, and rapid economic modernization (Spain joined the EU in 1986) gave Spain a dynamic and rapidly growing economy and made it a global champion of freedom and human rights. The government continues to battle the Basque Fatherland and Liberty (ETA) terrorist organization, but its major focus for the immediate future will be on measures to reverse the severe economic recession that started in mid-2008.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location along approaches to Strait of Gibraltar; Spain controls a number of territories in northern Morocco including the enclaves of Ceuta and Melilla, and the islands of Penon de Velez de la Gomera, Penon de Alhucemas, and Islas Chafarinas</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Southwestern Europe, bordering the Mediterranean Sea, North Atlantic Ocean, Bay of Biscay, and Pyrenees Mountains; southwest of France</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">505370</total>
			<land unit="sq km">498980</land>
			<water unit="sq km">6390</water>
			<comparison>slightly more than twice the size of Oregon</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">4964</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit="nm">24</contiguous>
			<economic unit="nm">200</economic>
			<continental-shelf></continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; clear, hot summers in interior, more moderate and cloudy along coast; cloudy, cold winters in interior, partly cloudy and cool along coast</climate>
		<terrain>large, flat to dissected plateau surrounded by rugged hills; Pyrenees Mountains in north</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Pico de Teide (Tenerife) on Canary Islands 3,718 m</high>
			<low>Atlantic Ocean 0 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, lignite, iron ore, copper, lead, zinc, uranium, tungsten, mercury, pyrites, magnesite, fluorspar, gypsum, sepiolite, kaolin, potash, hydropower, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">27.18</arable>
			<crops unit="%">9.85</crops>
			<other unit="%">62.97</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>[object Object]</hazards>
		<issues>pollution of the Mediterranean Sea from raw sewage and effluents from the offshore production of oil and gas; water quality and quantity nationwide; air pollution; deforestation; desertification</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">38000</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">111.1</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">37.22</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">864</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>46754</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.66</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">8.8</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">3.89</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.574</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.1</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">67.7</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>40.5</total>
			<male>39.3</male>
			<female>41.9</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">77</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">1</rate>
			<cities>MADRID (capital) 5.762 million; Barcelona 5.029 million; Valencia 812,000 (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.065</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.01</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.72</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.96</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.39</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.74</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">3.03</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.17</total>
			<male unit="years">78.16</male>
			<female unit="years">84.37</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.47">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>130000</total>
			<deaths>1600</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Spaniard(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Spanish</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>composite of Mediterranean and Nordic types</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Roman Catholic 94%, other 6%</religions>
		<languages>Castilian Spanish (official) 74%, Catalan 17%, Galician 7%, and Basque 2% (official regionally)</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">97.9</total>
			<male unit="%">98.7</male>
			<female unit="%">97.2</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">4.3</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Spain</long>
			<short>Spain</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>parliamentary monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Madrid</name>
			<coordinates>40° 24' N, 3° 41' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>1492; the Iberian peninsula was characterized by a variety of independent kingdoms prior to the Muslim occupation that began in the early 8th century A.D. and lasted nearly seven centuries; the small Christian redoubts of the north began the reconquest almost immediately, culminating in the seizure of Granada in 1492; this event completed the unification of several kingdoms and is traditionally considered the forging of present-day Spain</independence>
		<national-holiday>National Day, 12 October (1492); year when Columbus first set foot in the Americas</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system with regional variations</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King JUAN CARLOS I (since 22 November 1975); Heir Apparent Prince FELIPE, son of the monarch, born 30 January 1968</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>President of the Government (Prime Minister equivalent) Jose Luis Rodriguez ZAPATERO (since 17 April 2004); First Vice President (and Minister of the Interior) Alfredo Perez RUBALCABA (since 20 October 2010), Second Vice President (and Minister of Economy and Finance) Elena SALGADO Mendez (since 8 April 2009), and Third Vice President (and Minister of Regional Affairs) Manuel CHAVES Gonzalez (since 8 April 2009)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Council of Ministers designated by the president</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually proposed president by the monarch and elected by the National Assembly; election last held on 9 and 11 April 2008 (next to be held in March 2012); vice presidents appointed by the monarch on the proposal of the president</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral; General Courts or Las Cortes Generales (National Assembly) consists of the Senate or Senado (264 seats as of 2008; 208 members directly elected by popular vote and the other 56 - as of 2008 - appointed by the regional legislatures; members to serve four-year terms) and the Congress of Deputies or Congreso de los Diputados (350 seats; each of the 50 electoral provinces fills a minimum of two seats and the North African enclaves of Ceuta and Melilla fill one seat each with members serving a four-year term; the other 248 members are determined by proportional representation based on popular vote on block lists who serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>Senate - last held on 9 March 2008 (next to be held by March 2012); Congress of Deputies - last held on 9 March 2008 (next to be held by March 2012)</elections>
			<election-results>Senate - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - PP 101, PSOE 88, Entesa Catalona de Progress 12, CiU 4, PNV 2, CC 1, members appointed by regional legislatures 56; Congress of Deputies - percent of vote by party - PSOE 43.6%, PP 40.1%, CiU 3.1%, PNV 1.2%, ERC 1.2%, other 10.8%; seats by party - PSOE 169, PP 154, CiU 10, PNV 6, ERC 3, other 8; note - seats by party in the Congress of Deputies as of 15 December 2009 - PSOE 169, PP 153, CiU 10, PNV 6, ERC 3, other 9</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Tribunal Supremo</judicial>
		<parties>Basque Nationalist Party or PNV or EAJ [Inigo URKULLU Renteria]; Canarian Coalition or CC [Claudina MORALES Rodriquez] (a coalition of five parties); Convergence and Union or CiU [Artur MAS i Gavarro] (a coalition of the Democratic Convergence of Catalonia or CDC [Artur MAS i Gavarro] and the Democratic Union of Catalonia or UDC [Josep Antoni DURAN i LLEIDA]); Entesa Catalonia de Progress (a Senate coalition grouping four Catalan parties - PSC, ERC, ICV, EUA); Galician Nationalist Bloc or BNG [Guillerme VAZQUEZ Vazquez]; Initiative for Catalonia Greens or ICV [Joan SAURA i Laporta]; Navarra Yes or NaBai [collective leadership] (a coalition of four Navarran parties); Popular Party or PP [Mariano RAJOY Brey]; Republican Left of Catalonia or ERC [Joan PUIGCERCOS i Boixassa]; Spanish Socialist Workers Party or PSOE [Jose Luis Rodriguez ZAPATERO]; Union of People of Navarra or UPN [Yolanda BARCINA Angulo]; Union, Progress and Democracy or UPyD [Rosa DIEZ Gonzalez]; United Left or IU [Cayo LARA Moya] (a coalition of parties including the Communist Party of Spain or PCE and other small parties)</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, BCIE, BIS, CBSS (observer), CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, EMU, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, LAIA (observer), MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, Schengen Convention, SECI (observer), SICA (observer), UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, Union Latina, UNMIS, UNRWA, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jorge DEZCALLAR de Mazarredo</chief>
			<chancery>2375 Pennsylvania Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20037</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 452-0100, 728-2340</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 833-5670</FAX>
			<consulates>Boston, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New Orleans, New York, San Francisco, San Juan (Puerto Rico)</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Alan D. SOLOMONT</chief>
			<embassy>Serrano 75, 28006 Madrid</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 61, APO AE 09642</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[34] (91) 587-2200</telephone>
			<FAX>[34] (91) 587-2303</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>[object Object]</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Himno Nacional Espanol&quot; (National Anthem of Spain)</name>
			<by>none/unknown</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Spain's mixed capitalist economy is the 12th largest in the world, and its per capita income roughly matches that of Germany and France. However, after almost 15 years of above average GDP growth, the Spanish economy began to slow in late 2007 and entered into a recession in the second quarter of 2008. GDP contracted by 3.7% in 2009, ending a 16-year growth trend, and by another 0.2% in 2010, making Spain the last major economy to emerge from the global recession. The reversal in Spain's economic growth reflected a significant decline in construction amid an oversupply of housing and falling consumer spending, while exports actually have begun to grow. Government efforts to boost the economy through stimulus spending, extended unemployment benefits, and loan guarantees did not prevent a sharp rise in the unemployment rate, which rose from a low of about 8% in 2007 to 20% in 2010. The government budget deficit worsened from 3.8% of GDP in 2008 to about 9.7% of GDP in 2010, more than three times the euro-zone limit. Spain's large budget deficit and poor economic growth prospects have made it vulnerable to financial contagion from other highly-indebted euro zone members despite the government's efforts to cut spending, privatize industries, and boost competitiveness through labor market reforms. Spanish banks' high exposure to the collapsed domestic construction and real estate market also poses a continued risk for the sector. The government oversaw a restructuring of the savings bank sector in 2010, and provided some $15 billion in capital to various institutions. Investors remain concerned that Madrid may need to bail out more troubled banks. The Bank of Spain, however, is seeking to boost confidence in the financial sector by pressuring banks to come clean about their losses and consolidate into stronger groups.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>1410000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit=""></real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>22960000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">20</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">63.4</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">10.72</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD"></narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">2264000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">3683000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>grain, vegetables, olives, wine grapes, sugar beets, citrus; beef, pork, poultry, dairy products; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>textiles and apparel (including footwear), food and beverages, metals and metal manufactures, chemicals, shipbuilding, automobiles, machine tools, tourism, clay and refractory products, footwear, pharmaceuticals, medical equipment</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>-2% (2010 est.)</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>300500000000</production>
			<consumption>276100000000</consumption>
			<exports>16920000000.000002</exports>
			<imports>5880000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">27230</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">1482000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">218600</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">1716000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">150000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">13000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">33880000000.000004</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">975000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">34670000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">2548000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery, motor vehicles; foodstuffs, pharmaceuticals, medicines, other consumer goods</commodities>
			<partners>France 19.27%, Germany 11.11%, Portugal 9.21%, Italy 8.24%, UK 6.18% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">324600000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery and equipment, fuels, chemicals, semifinished goods, foodstuffs, consumer goods, measuring and medical control instruments</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 15.02%, France 12.82%, Italy 7.17%, China 5.8%, Netherlands 5.22%, UK 4.7% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">2166000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>euros (EUR) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>well developed, modern facilities; fixed-line teledensity is roughly 50 per 100 persons</assessment>
			<domestic>combined fixed-line and mobile-cellular teledensity is nearly 175 telephones per 100 persons</domestic>
			<international>country code - 34; submarine cables provide connectivity to Europe, Middle East, Asia, and US; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (1 Atlantic Ocean and 1 Indian Ocean), NA Eutelsat; tropospheric scatter to adjacent countries</international>
			<land-lines>20057000</land-lines>
			<mobile>50991000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>a mixture of both publicly-operated and privately-owned TV and radio stations broadcasting; overall, hundreds of TV channels are available including national, regional, local, public, and international channels; satellite and cable TV systems are accessible; multiple national radio networks, a large number of regional radio networks, and a larger number of local radio stations broadcasting; overall, hundreds of radio stations operating (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.es</tld>
			<hosts>3822000</hosts>
			<users>28119000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>154</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">13</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">18</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">24</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Algeciras, Barcelona, Bilbao, Cartagena, Huelva, Tarragona, Valencia (Spain); Las Palmas, Santa Cruz de Tenerife (Canary Islands)</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Spanish Armed Forces: Army (Ejercito de Tierra), Spanish Navy (Armada Espanola, AE; includes Marine Corps), Spanish Air Force (Ejercito del Aire Espanola, EdA) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>11759</male>
				<female>11204</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>9603</male>
				<female>9116</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>217244</male>
				<female>205278</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>in 2002, Gibraltar residents voted overwhelmingly by referendum to reject any &quot;shared sovereignty&quot; arrangement; the government of Gibraltar insists on equal participation in talks between the UK and Spain; Spain disapproves of UK plans to grant Gibraltar greater autonomy; Morocco protests Spain's control over the coastal enclaves of Ceuta, Melilla, and the islands of Penon de Velez de la Gomera, Penon de Alhucemas, and Islas Chafarinas, and surrounding waters; both countries claim Isla Perejil (Leila Island); Morocco serves as the primary launching site of illegal migration into Spain from North Africa; Portugal does not recognize Spanish sovereignty over the territory of Olivenza based on a difference of interpretation of the 1815 Congress of Vienna and the 1801 Treaty of Badajoz</disputes>
		<drugs>despite rigorous law enforcement efforts, North African, Latin American, Galician, and other European traffickers take advantage of Spain's long coastline to land large shipments of cocaine and hashish for distribution to the European market; consumer for Latin American cocaine and North African hashish; destination and minor transshipment point for Southwest Asian heroin; money-laundering site for Colombian narcotics trafficking organizations and organized crime</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>sw</code>
	<name>Sweden</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>A military power during the 17th century, Sweden has not participated in any war for almost two centuries. An armed neutrality was preserved in both world wars. Sweden's long-successful economic formula of a capitalist system interlarded with substantial welfare elements was challenged in the 1990s by high unemployment and in 2000-02 and 2009 by the global economic downturns, but fiscal discipline over the past several years has allowed the country to weather economic vagaries. Sweden joined the EU in 1995, but the public rejected the introduction of the euro in a 2003 referendum.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>strategic location along Danish Straits linking Baltic and North Seas</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Northern Europe, bordering the Baltic Sea, Gulf of Bothnia, Kattegat, and Skagerrak, between Finland and Norway</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">450295</total>
			<land unit="sq km">410335</land>
			<water unit="sq km">39960</water>
			<comparison>slightly larger than California</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">3218</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>200 m depth or to the depth of exploitation</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate in south with cold, cloudy winters and cool, partly cloudy summers; subarctic in north</climate>
		<terrain>mostly flat or gently rolling lowlands; mountains in west</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Kebnekaise 2,111 m</high>
			<low>reclaimed bay of Lake Hammarsjon, near Kristianstad -2.4 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>iron ore, copper, lead, zinc, gold, silver, tungsten, uranium, arsenic, feldspar, timber, hydropower</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">5.93</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.01</crops>
			<other unit="%">94.06</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>ice floes in the surrounding waters, especially in the Gulf of Bothnia, can interfere with maritime traffic</hazards>
		<issues>acid rain damage to soils and lakes; pollution of the North Sea and the Baltic Sea</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1600</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">179</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">2.68</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">296</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>9088</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">10.18</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">10.2</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">1.65</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.163</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">15.4</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">64.8</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>42</total>
			<male>40.8</male>
			<female>43.1</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">85</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.6</rate>
			<cities>STOCKHOLM (capital) 1.279 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.061</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.06</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.02</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.8</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.98</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">2.74</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">2.9</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">2.57</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">81.07</total>
			<male unit="years">78.78</male>
			<female unit="years">83.51</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.67">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>8100</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 100 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Swede(s)</noun>
			<adjective>Swedish</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>indigenous population: Swedes with Finnish and Sami minorities; foreign-born or first-generation immigrants: Finns, Yugoslavs, Danes, Norwegians, Greeks, Turks</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Lutheran 87%, other (includes Roman Catholic, Orthodox, Baptist, Muslim, Jewish, and Buddhist) 13%</religions>
		<languages>Swedish (official), small Sami- and Finnish-speaking minorities</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">6.6</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>Kingdom of Sweden</long>
			<short>Sweden</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional monarchy</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>Stockholm</name>
			<coordinates>59° 20' N, 18° 3' E</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>21 counties (lan, singular and plural); Blekinge, Dalarna, Gavleborg, Gotland, Halland, Jamtland, Jonkoping, Kalmar, Kronoberg, Norrbotten, Orebro, Ostergotland, Skane, Sodermanland, Stockholm, Uppsala, Varmland, Vasterbotten, Vasternorrland, Vastmanland, Vastra Gotaland</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>6 June 1523 (Gustav VASA elected king)</independence>
		<national-holiday>Swedish Flag Day, 6 June (1916); National Day, 6 June (1983)</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>civil law system influenced by Roman-Germanic law and customary law</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>King CARL XVI GUSTAF (since 19 September 1973); Heir Apparent Princess VICTORIA Ingrid Alice Desiree, daughter of the monarch (born 14 July 1977)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister Fredrik REINFELDT (since 5 October 2006); Deputy Prime Minister Jan BJORKLUND (since 5 October 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet appointed by the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually becomes the prime minister</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>unicameral Parliament or Riksdag (349 seats; members are elected by popular vote on a proportional representation basis to serve four-year terms)</description>
			<elections>last held on 19 September 2010 (next to be held in September 2014)</elections>
			<election-results>percent of vote by party - Social Democrats 30.7%, Moderates 30.1%, Greens 7.3%, Liberal People's Party 7.1%, Center Party 6.6%, Sweden Democrats 5.7%, Christian Democrats 5.6%, Left Party 5.6%, others 1.3%; seats by party - Social Democrats 112, Moderates 107, Greens 25, Liberal People's Party 24, Center Party 23, Sweden Democrats 20, Christian Democrats 19, Left Party 19</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court or Hogsta Domstolen (judges are appointed by the prime minister and the cabinet)</judicial>
		<parties>Center Party [Maud OLOFSSON]; Christian Democratic Party [Goran HAGGLUND]; Environment Party the Greens [no formal leader but party spokespersons are Maria WETTERSTRAND and Peter ERIKSSON]; Left Party or V (formerly Communist) [Lars OHLY]; Liberal People's Party [Jan BJORKLUND]; Moderate Party [Fredrik REINFELDT]; Social Democratic Party [Mona SAHLIN]; Sweden Democrats [Jimmie AKESSON]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council, Australia Group, BIS, CBSS, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-9, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NC, NEA, NIB, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PFP, Schengen Convention, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNMOGIP, UNRWA, UNTSO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Jonas HAFSTROM</chief>
			<chancery>The House of Sweden, 2900 K Street NW, Washington, DC 20007</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 467-2600</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 467-2699</FAX>
			<consulates>New York</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Matthew W. BARZUN</chief>
			<embassy>Dag Hammarskjolds Vag 31, SE-11589 Stockholm</embassy>
			<mailing-address>American Embassy Stockholm, US Department of State, 5750 Stockholm Place, Washington, DC 20521-5750</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[46] (08) 783 53 00</telephone>
			<FAX>[46] (08) 661 19 64</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>blue with a golden yellow cross extending to the edges of the flag; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side in the style of the Dannebrog (Danish flag); the colors reflect those of the Swedish coat of arms - three gold crowns on a blue field</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;Du Gamla, Du Fria&quot; (Thou Ancient, Thou Free)</name>
			<by>Richard DYBECK/traditional</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>Aided by peace and neutrality for the whole of the 20th century, Sweden has achieved an enviable standard of living under a mixed system of high-tech capitalism and extensive welfare benefits. It has a modern distribution system, excellent internal and external communications, and a skilled labor force. In September 2003, Swedish voters turned down entry into the euro system concerned about the impact on the economy and sovereignty. Timber, hydropower, and iron ore constitute the resource base of an economy heavily oriented toward foreign trade. Privately owned firms account for about 90% of industrial output, of which the engineering sector accounts for 50% of output and exports. Agriculture accounts for little more than 1% of GDP and of employment. Until 2008, Sweden was in the midst of a sustained economic upswing, boosted by increased domestic demand and strong exports. This and robust finances offered the center-right government considerable scope to implement its reform program aimed at increasing employment, reducing welfare dependence, and streamlining the state's role in the economy. Despite strong finances and underlying fundamentals, the Swedish economy slid into recession in the third quarter of 2008 and growth continued downward in 2009 as deteriorating global conditions reduced export demand and consumption. Strong exports of commodities and a return to profitability by Sweden's banking sector drove the strong rebound in 2010.</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>455800000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">5.5</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>4930000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">8.3</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>NA%</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">40.8</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">1.4</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%">2</central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%"></commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">225000000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">293200000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">640200000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>barley, wheat, sugar beets; meat, milk</agriculture-products>
		<industries>iron and steel, precision equipment (bearings, radio and telephone parts, armaments), wood pulp and paper products, processed foods, motor vehicles</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>144000000000</production>
			<consumption>134500000000</consumption>
			<exports>14710000000</exports>
			<imports>12750000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">4833</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">328100</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">248500</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">589900</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">0</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">0</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">1229000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">0</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">1229000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">0</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>machinery 35%, motor vehicles, paper products, pulp and wood, iron and steel products, chemicals</commodities>
			<partners>Norway 10.61%, Germany 10.2%, UK 7.45%, Denmark 7.35%, Finland 6.44%, US 6.36%, France 5.05%, Netherlands 4.67% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">158600000000</total>
			<commodities>machinery, petroleum and petroleum products, chemicals, motor vehicles, iron and steel; foodstuffs, clothing</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 17.9%, Denmark 8.9%, Norway 8.7%, Netherlands 6.17%, UK 5.56%, Finland 5.14%, France 5.06%, China 4.79% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">853300000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>Swedish kronor (SEK) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>highly developed telecommunications infrastructure; ranked among leading countries for fixed-line, mobile-cellular, Internet and broadband penetration</assessment>
			<domestic>coaxial and multiconductor cables carry most of the voice traffic; parallel microwave radio relay systems carry some additional telephone channels</domestic>
			<international>country code - 46; submarine cables provide links to other Nordic countries and Europe; satellite earth stations - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean), 1 Eutelsat, and 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic and Indian Ocean regions); note - Sweden shares the Inmarsat earth station with the other Nordic countries (Denmark, Finland, Iceland, and Norway)</international>
			<land-lines>5146000</land-lines>
			<mobile>11426000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>publicly-owned television broadcaster operates 2 terrestrial networks plus regional stations; multiple privately-owned television broadcasters operating nationally, regionally, and locally; about 50 local TV stations; widespread access to pan-Nordic and international broadcasters through multi-channel cable and satellite TV systems; publicly-owned radio broadcaster operates 3 national stations and a network of 25 regional channels; nearly a hundred privately-owned local radio stations with some consolidating into near national networks; an estimated 900 community and neighborhood radio stations broadcast intermittently (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.se</tld>
			<hosts>4396000</hosts>
			<users>8398000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>249</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">3</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">12</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">76</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">25</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Brofjorden, Goteborg, Helsingborg, Karlshamn, Lulea, Malmo, Stockholm, Trelleborg, Visby</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Swedish Armed Forces (Forsvarsmakten): Army (Armen), Royal Swedish Navy (Marinen), Swedish Air Force (Svenska Flygvapnet) (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>2065</male>
				<female>1996</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>1709</male>
				<female>1650</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>54960</male>
				<female>52275</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>none</disputes>
		<drugs></drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
<country>
	<code>uk</code>
	<name>United Kingdom</name>
	<region>Europe</region>
	<background>The United Kingdom has historically played a leading role in developing parliamentary democracy and in advancing literature and science. At its zenith in the 19th century, the British Empire stretched over one-fourth of the earth's surface. The first half of the 20th century saw the UK's strength seriously depleted in two world wars and the Irish republic withdraw from the union. The second half witnessed the dismantling of the Empire and the UK rebuilding itself into a modern and prosperous European nation. As one of five permanent members of the UN Security Council, a founding member of NATO, and of the Commonwealth, the UK pursues a global approach to foreign policy. The UK is also an active member of the EU, although it chose to remain outside the Economic and Monetary Union. The Scottish Parliament, the National Assembly for Wales, and the Northern Ireland Assembly were established in 1999. The latter was suspended until May 2007 due to wrangling over the peace process, but devolution was fully completed in March 2010.</background>
	<geo>
		<note>lies near vital North Atlantic sea lanes; only 35 km from France and linked by tunnel under the English Channel; because of heavily indented coastline, no location is more than 125 km from tidal waters</note>
		<location>
			<desc>Western Europe, islands - including the northern one-sixth of the island of Ireland - between the North Atlantic Ocean and the North Sea; northwest of France</desc>
			<coordinates>TO DO</coordinates>
		</location>
		<area>
			<total unit="sq km">243610</total>
			<land unit="sq km">241930</land>
			<water unit="sq km">1680</water>
			<comparison>slightly smaller than Oregon</comparison>
		</area>
		<boundaries>
			<borders unit=""></borders>
			<coastline unit="km">12429</coastline>
		</boundaries>
		<maritime-claims>
			<territorial unit="nm">12</territorial>
			<contiguous unit=""></contiguous>
			<economic unit=""></economic>
			<continental-shelf>as defined in continental shelf orders or in accordance with agreed upon boundaries</continental-shelf>
		</maritime-claims>
		<climate>temperate; moderated by prevailing southwest winds over the North Atlantic Current; more than one-half of the days are overcast</climate>
		<terrain>mostly rugged hills and low mountains; level to rolling plains in east and southeast</terrain>
		<elevation>
			<high>Ben Nevis 1,343 m</high>
			<low>The Fens -4 m</low>
		</elevation>
		<resources>coal, petroleum, natural gas, iron ore, lead, zinc, gold, tin, limestone, salt, clay, chalk, gypsum, potash, silica sand, slate, arable land</resources>
		<land-use>
			<arable unit="%">23.23</arable>
			<crops unit="%">0.2</crops>
			<other unit="%">76.57</other>
		</land-use>
		<hazards>winter windstorms; floods</hazards>
		<issues>continues to reduce greenhouse gas emissions (has met Kyoto Protocol target of a 12.5% reduction from 1990 levels and intends to meet the legally binding target and move toward a domestic goal of a 20% cut in emissions by 2010); by 2005 the government reduced the amount of industrial and commercial waste disposed of in landfill sites to 85% of 1998 levels and recycled or composted at least 25% of household waste, increasing to 33% by 2015</issues>
		<water>
			<irrigated-land unit="sq km">1950</irrigated-land>
			<renewable-water unit="cu km">160.6</renewable-water>
			<freshwater-withdrawal>
				<total unit="cu km/yr">11.75</total>
				<per-capita unit="cu m/yr">197</per-capita>
			</freshwater-withdrawal>
		</water>
		<!--
"geo": {

		"Natural hazards": "flooding is a threat in some areas of the country (e.g., parts of Jutland, along the southern coast of the island of Lolland) that are protected from the sea by a system of dikes",
		"Environment - current issues": "air pollution, principally from vehicle and power plant emissions; nitrogen and phosphorus pollution of the North Sea; drinking and surface water becoming polluted from animal wastes and pesticides",
		"Environment - international agreements": {
			"party to:": "Air Pollution, Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides, Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants, Air Pollution-Sulfur 85, Air Pollution-Sulfur 94, Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds, Antarctic Treaty, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping, Marine Life Conservation, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Tropical Timber 83, Tropical Timber 94, Wetlands, Whaling",
			"signed, but not ratified:": "none of the selected agreements"
		},
		"Geography - note": "controls Danish Straits (Skagerrak and Kattegat) linking Baltic and North Seas; about one-quarter of the population lives in greater Copenhagen"

		-->
	</geo>
	<people>
		<population>
			<total>62698</total>
			<birth unit="births/1,000 population">12.29</birth>
			<death unit="deaths/1,000 population">9.33</death>
			<migration unit="migrant(s)/1,000 population">2.6</migration>
			<growth unit="%">0.557</growth>
		</population>
		<age-distribution unit="percent">
			<group min="0" max="14">17.3</group>
			<group min="15" max="64">66.2</group>
			<group min="65"></group>
		</age-distribution>
		<median-age unit="years">
			<total>40</total>
			<male>38.8</male>
			<female>41.1</female>
		</median-age>
		<urbanization>
			<urban unit="% of total population">80</urban>
			<rate unit="% annual rate of change">0.7</rate>
			<cities>LONDON (capital) 8.615 million; Birmingham 2.296 million; Manchester 2.247 million; West Yorkshire 1.541 million; Glasgow 1.166 million (2009)</cities>
		</urbanization>
		<sex unit="male(s)/female">
			<group name="at birth" max="0">1.052</group>
			<group name="0 to 14" min="0" max="14">1.05</group>
			<group name="15 to 64" min="15" max="64">1.03</group>
			<group name="65 and over" min="65" max="0">0.76</group>
			<group name="total" min="0">0.98</group>
		</sex>
		<infant-mortality>
			<total unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.62</total>
			<male unit="deaths/1,000 live births">5.07</male>
			<female unit="deaths/1,000 live births">4.15</female>
		</infant-mortality>
		<life-expectancy-at-birth>
			<total unit="years">80.05</total>
			<male unit="years">77.95</male>
			<female unit="years">82.25</female>
		</life-expectancy-at-birth>
		<fertility-rate unit="1.91">children born/woman</fertility-rate>
		<hiv>
			<prevalence>[object Object]</prevalence>
			<total>85000</total>
			<deaths>fewer than 1,000 (2009 est.)</deaths>
		</hiv>
		<infectious-disease risk="">
			<food-or-waterborne></food-or-waterborne>
			<vectorborne></vectorborne>
			<water-contact></water-contact>
		</infectious-disease>
		<drinking-water-source>[object Object]</drinking-water-source>
		<sanitation-access>[object Object]</sanitation-access>
		<nationality>
			<noun>Briton(s), British (collective plural)</noun>
			<adjective>British</adjective>
		</nationality>
		<ethnic-groups>white (of which English 83.6%, Scottish 8.6%, Welsh 4.9%, Northern Irish 2.9%) 92.1%, black 2%, Indian 1.8%, Pakistani 1.3%, mixed 1.2%, other 1.6% (2001 census)</ethnic-groups>
		<religions>Christian (Anglican, Roman Catholic, Presbyterian, Methodist) 71.6%, Muslim 2.7%, Hindu 1%, other 1.6%, unspecified or none 23.1% (2001 census)</religions>
		<languages>English</languages>
		<literacy>
			<definition>age 15 and over has completed five or more years of schooling</definition>
			<total unit="%">99</total>
			<male unit="%">99</male>
			<female unit="%">99</female>
		</literacy>
		<school-expectancy unit="years">16</school-expectancy>
		<education-expenditure unit="% of GDP">5.5</education-expenditure>
	</people>
	<government>
		<country-name>
			<long>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland; note - Great Britain includes England, Scotland, and Wales</long>
			<short>United Kingdom</short>
		</country-name>
		<dependency></dependency>
		<government-type>constitutional monarchy and Commonwealth realm</government-type>
		<capital>
			<name>London</name>
			<coordinates>51° 30' N, 0° 10' W</coordinates>
			<time-difference>UTC 0 (5 hours ahead of Washington, DC during Standard Time)</time-difference>
		</capital>
		<administrative-divisions>[object Object]</administrative-divisions>
		<independence>12 April 1927 (Royal and Parliamentary Titles Act establishes current name of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland); notable earlier dates: 927 (minor English kingdoms united); 3 March 1284 (enactment of the Statute of Rhuddlan uniting England and Wales); 1536 (Act of Union formally incorporates England and Wales); 1 May 1707 (Acts of Union formally unite England and Scotland as Great Britain); 1 January 1801 (Acts of Union formally unite Great Britain and Ireland as the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland); 6 December 1921 (Anglo-Irish Treaty formalizes partition of Ireland; six counties remain part of the United Kingdom as Northern Ireland)</independence>
		<national-holiday>the UK does not celebrate one particular national holiday</national-holiday>
		<legal-system>common law system; has nonbinding judicial review of Acts of Parliament under the Human Rights Act of 1998</legal-system>
		<suffrage>18 years of age; universal</suffrage>
		<executive>
			<head-of-state>Queen ELIZABETH II (since 6 February 1952); Heir Apparent Prince CHARLES (son of the queen, born 14 November 1948)</head-of-state>
			<head-of-government>Prime Minister David CAMERON (since 11 May 2010)</head-of-government>
			<cabinet>Cabinet of Ministers appointed by the prime minister</cabinet>
			<elections>the monarchy is hereditary; following legislative elections, the leader of the majority party or the leader of the majority coalition usually the prime minister</elections>
			<election-results></election-results>
		</executive>
		<legislative>
			<description>bicameral Parliament consists of House of Lords (741 seats; consisting of approximately 625 life peers, 91 hereditary peers, and 25 clergy - as of 15 December 2010) and House of Commons (650 seats since 2010 elections; members elected by popular vote to serve five-year terms unless the House is dissolved earlier)</description>
			<elections>House of Lords - no elections (note - in 1999, as provided by the House of Lords Act, elections were held in the House of Lords to determine the 92 hereditary peers who would remain there; elections are held only as vacancies in the hereditary peerage arise); House of Commons - last held on 6 May 2010 (next to be held by June 2015)</elections>
			<election-results>House of Commons - percent of vote by party - Conservative 36.1%, Labor 29%, Liberal Democrats 23%, other 11.9%; seats by party - Conservative 305, Labor 258, Liberal Democrat 57, other 30</election-results>
		</legislative>
		<judicial>Supreme Court of the UK (established in October 2009 taking over appellate jurisdiction formerly vested in the House of Lords); Senior Courts of England and Wales (comprising the Court of Appeal, the High Court of Justice, and the Crown Courts); Court of Judicature (Northern Ireland); Scotland's Court of Session and High Court of the Justiciary</judicial>
		<parties>Conservative [David CAMERON]; Democratic Unionist Party or DUP (Northern Ireland) [Peter ROBINSON]; Labor Party [Ed MILIBAND]; Liberal Democrats (Lib Dems) [Nick CLEGG]; Party of Wales (Plaid Cymru) [Ieuan Wyn JONES]; Scottish National Party or SNP [Alex SALMOND]; Sinn Fein (Northern Ireland) [Gerry ADAMS]; Social Democratic and Labor Party or SDLP (Northern Ireland) [Margaret RICHIE]; Ulster Unionist Party (Northern Ireland) [Tom ELLIOTT]</parties>
		<pressure-groups>TO DO</pressure-groups>
		<membership>ADB (nonregional member), AfDB (nonregional member), Arctic Council (observer), Australia Group, BIS, C, CBSS (observer), CDB, CE, CERN, EAPC, EBRD, EIB, ESA, EU, FAO, FATF, G-20, G-5, G-7, G-8, G-10, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC, ICRM, IDA, IEA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC, MIGA, MONUSCO, NATO, NEA, NSG, OAS (observer), OECD, OPCW, OSCE, Paris Club, PCA, PIF (partner), SECI (observer), UN, UN Security Council, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNMIS, UNRWA, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, ZC</membership>
		<representation-in-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Sir Nigel E. SHEINWALD</chief>
			<chancery>3100 Massachusetts Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20008</chancery>
			<telephone>[1] (202) 588-6500</telephone>
			<FAX>[1] (202) 588-7870</FAX>
			<consulates>Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, San Francisco</consulates>
		</representation-in-usa>
		<representation-from-usa>
			<chief>Ambassador Louis B. SUSMAN</chief>
			<embassy>24 Grosvenor Square, London, W1A 1AE note - a new embassy is scheduled to open by the end of 2017 in the Nine Elms area of Wandsworth (architect Kiernan TIMBERLAKE)</embassy>
			<mailing-address>PSC 801, Box 40, FPO AE 09498-4040</mailing-address>
			<telephone>[44] (0) 20 7499-9000</telephone>
			<FAX>[44] (0) 20 7629-9124</FAX>
		</representation-from-usa>
		<flag>blue field with the red cross of Saint George (patron saint of England) edged in white superimposed on the diagonal red cross of Saint Patrick (patron saint of Ireland), which is superimposed on the diagonal white cross of Saint Andrew (patron saint of Scotland); properly known as the Union Flag, but commonly called the Union Jack; the design and colors (especially the Blue Ensign) have been the basis for a number of other flags including other Commonwealth countries and their constituent states or provinces, and British overseas territories</flag>
		<anthem>
			<name>&quot;God Save the Queen&quot;</name>
			<by>unknown</by>
		</anthem>
	</government>
	<economy>
		<overview>The UK, a leading trading power and financial center, is the third largest economy in Europe after Germany and France. Over the past two decades, the government has greatly reduced public ownership and contained the growth of social welfare programs. Agriculture is intensive, highly mechanized, and efficient by European standards, producing about 60% of food needs with less than 2% of the labor force. The UK has large coal, natural gas, and oil resources, but its oil and natural gas reserves are declining and the UK became a net importer of energy in 2005. Services, particularly banking, insurance, and business services, account by far for the largest proportion of GDP while industry continues to decline in importance. After emerging from recession in 1992, Britain's economy enjoyed the longest period of expansion on record during which time growth outpaced most of Western Europe. In 2008, however, the global financial crisis hit the economy particularly hard, due to the importance of its financial sector. Sharply declining home prices, high consumer debt, and the global economic slowdown compounded Britain's economic problems, pushing the economy into recession in the latter half of 2008 and prompting the then BROWN government to implement a number of measures to stimulate the economy and stabilize the financial markets; these include nationalizing parts of the banking system, cutting taxes, suspending public sector borrowing rules, and moving forward public spending on capital projects. Facing burgeoning public deficits and debt levels, the CAMERON government in 2010 initiated a five-year austerity program, which aims to lower London's budget deficit from over 11% of GDP in 2010 to nearly 1% by 2015. The Bank of England periodically coordinates interest rate moves with the European Central Bank, but Britain remains outside the European Economic and Monetary Union (EMU).</overview>
		<gdp>
			<purchasing-power-parity></purchasing-power-parity>
			<official-exchange-rate>2247000000000</official-exchange-rate>
			<real-growth-rate unit="%">1.3</real-growth-rate>
			<per-capita></per-capita>
			<sector unit="%">
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
		</gdp>
		<labour>
			<force>31450000</force>
			<sector>
				<agriculture></agriculture>
				<industry></industry>
				<services></services>
			</sector>
			<unemployment unit="%">7.9</unemployment>
		</labour>
		<poverty>[object Object]</poverty>
		<household-income>TO DO</household-income>
		<budget>
			<revenue unit="USD"></revenue>
			<expenditure unit="USD"></expenditure>
		</budget>
		<public-debt unit="% of GDP">76.5</public-debt>
		<consumer-inflation unit="%">3.3</consumer-inflation>
		<central-bank-discount-rate unit="%"></central-bank-discount-rate>
		<commercial-prime-lending-rate unit="%">0.63</commercial-prime-lending-rate>
		<narrow-money-stock unit="USD">88620000000</narrow-money-stock>
		<broad-money-stock unit="USD">3344000000000</broad-money-stock>
		<domestic-credit-stock unit="USD">5151000000000</domestic-credit-stock>
		<agriculture-products>cereals, oilseed, potatoes, vegetables; cattle, sheep, poultry; fish</agriculture-products>
		<industries>machine tools, electric power equipment, automation equipment, railroad equipment, shipbuilding, aircraft, motor vehicles and parts, electronics and communications equipment, metals, chemicals, coal, petroleum, paper and paper products, food processing, textiles, clothing, other consumer goods</industries>
		<industrial-production-growth>[object Object]</industrial-production-growth>
		<electricity unit="kWh">
			<production>368600000000</production>
			<consumption>345800000000</consumption>
			<exports>1272000000</exports>
			<imports>12290000000</imports>
		</electricity>
		<oil>
			<production unit="bbl/day">1502000</production>
			<consumption unit="bbl/day">1669000</consumption>
			<exports unit="bbl/day">1393000</exports>
			<imports unit="bbl/day">1491000</imports>
			<reserves unit="bbl">3084000000</reserves>
		</oil>
		<natural-gas>
			<production unit="cu m">58560000000</production>
			<consumption unit="cu m">87450000000</consumption>
			<exports unit="cu m">12170000000</exports>
			<imports unit="cu m">41060000000</imports>
			<reserves unit="cu m">292000000000</reserves>
		</natural-gas>
		<exports>
			<total unit="USD"></total>
			<commodities>manufactured goods, fuels, chemicals; food, beverages, tobacco</commodities>
			<partners>US 14.71%, Germany 11.06%, France 8%, Netherlands 7.79%, Ireland 6.89%, Belgium 4.65%, Spain 4% (2009)</partners>
		</exports>
		<imports>
			<total unit="USD">546500000000</total>
			<commodities>manufactured goods, machinery, fuels; foodstuffs</commodities>
			<partners>Germany 12.87%, US 9.74%, China 8.88%, Netherlands 6.94%, France 6.64%, Belgium 4.86%, Norway 4.84%, Ireland 4.01%, Italy 3.99% (2009)</partners>
		</imports>
		<external-debt unit="USD">8981000000000</external-debt>
		<exchange-rates>British pounds (GBP) per US dollar -</exchange-rates>
	</economy>
	<communications>
		<telephones>
			<assessment>technologically advanced domestic and international system</assessment>
			<domestic>equal mix of buried cables, microwave radio relay, and fiber-optic systems</domestic>
			<international>country code - 44; numerous submarine cables provide links throughout Europe, Asia, Australia, the Middle East, and US; satellite earth stations - 10 Intelsat (7 Atlantic Ocean and 3 Indian Ocean), 1 Inmarsat (Atlantic Ocean region), and 1 Eutelsat; at least 8 large international switching centers</international>
			<land-lines>32116999.999999996</land-lines>
			<mobile>80375000</mobile>
		</telephones>
		<broadcast>public service broadcaster BBC is the largest broadcasting corporation in the world; BBC operates multiple TV networks with regional and local TV service; a mixed system of public and commercial TV broadcasters along with satellite and cable systems provide access to hundreds of TV stations throughout the world; BBC operates multiple national, regional, and local radio networks with multiple transmission sites; a large number of commercial radio stations as well as satellite radio services are available (2008)</broadcast>
		<internet>
			<tld>.uk</tld>
			<hosts>7030000</hosts>
			<users>51444000</users>
		</internet>
	</communications>
	<transport>
		<airports>
			<total>505</total>
			<paved>
				<altitude min="*" max="*"></altitude>
				<altitude min="3047m" max="*">9</altitude>
				<altitude min="2438m" max="3047m">32</altitude>
				<altitude min="1524m" max="2437m">124</altitude>
				<altitude min="914m" max="1524m">77</altitude>
				<altitude min="*" max="914m"></altitude>
			</paved>
		</airports>
		<ports-and-terminals>Dover, Felixstowe, Immingham, Liverpool, London, Southampton, Teesport (England); Forth Ports, Hound Point (Scotland); Milford Haven (Wales)</ports-and-terminals>
	</transport>
	<military>
		<branches>Army, Royal Navy (includes Royal Marines), Royal Air Force (2010)</branches>
		<manpower>
			<population-available>
				<male>14856</male>
				<female>14307</female>
			</population-available>
			<fit-for-service>
				<male>12255</male>
				<female>11779</female>
			</fit-for-service>
			<reaching-maturity>
				<male>383989</male>
				<female>365491</female>
			</reaching-maturity>
			<notes></notes>
		</manpower>
	</military>
	<issues>
		<disputes>in 2002, Gibraltar residents voted overwhelmingly by referendum to reject any &quot;shared sovereignty&quot; arrangement between the UK and Spain; the Government of Gibraltar insists on equal participation in talks between the two countries; Spain disapproves of UK plans to grant Gibraltar greater autonomy; Mauritius and Seychelles claim the Chagos Archipelago (British Indian Ocean Territory); in 2001, the former inhabitants of the archipelago, evicted 1967 - 1973, were granted U.K. citizenship and the right of return, followed by Orders in Council in 2004 that banned rehabitation, a High Court ruling reversing the ban, a Court of Appeal refusal to hear the case, and a Law Lords' decision in 2008 denying the right of return; in addition, the United Kingdom created the world's largest marine protection area around the Chagos islands prohibiting the extraction of any natural resources therein; UK rejects sovereignty talks requested by Argentina, which still claims the Falkland Islands (Islas Malvinas) and South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands; territorial claim in Antarctica (British Antarctic Territory) overlaps Argentine claim and partially overlaps Chilean claim; Iceland, the UK, and Ireland dispute Denmark's claim that the Faroe Islands' continental shelf extends beyond 200 nm</disputes>
		<drugs>producer of limited amounts of synthetic drugs and synthetic precursor chemicals; major consumer of Southwest Asian heroin, Latin American cocaine, and synthetic drugs; money-laundering center</drugs>
	</issues>
</country>
</countries>
